<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The King on his throne: or A discourse maintaining the dignity of a king, the duty of a subject, and the unlawfulnesse of rebellion. Delivered in two sermons preached in the Cathedrall Church in York. By R.M. Master in Arts, Coll. S. Pet. Cant.</title>
            <author>Mossom, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51440</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M2862</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R214245</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99826448</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99826448</idno>
            <idno type="VID">30851</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51440)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 30851)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1765:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The King on his throne: or A discourse maintaining the dignity of a king, the duty of a subject, and the unlawfulnesse of rebellion. Delivered in two sermons preached in the Cathedrall Church in York. By R.M. Master in Arts, Coll. S. Pet. Cant.</title>
                  <author>Mossom, Robert, d. 1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 46 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Stephen Bulkley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at York :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642. By speciall command.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: R. Mossom.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XXX, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Allegiance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:30851:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE KING ON HIS THRONE: OR A Diſcourſe maintaining the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of a <hi>KING,</hi> the Duty of a Subject, and the unlawfulneſſe of Rebellion.</p>
            <p>Delivered in two Sermons Preached in the <hi>Cathedrall Church</hi> in <hi>York.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>R. M.</hi> Maſter in Arts, <hi>Coll. S. Fet. Cant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>York</hi> by <hi>Stephen Bulkley,</hi> 1642.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By ſpeciall Command.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30851:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:30851:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, HENRY Earle of <hi>Cumberland,</hi> Lieutenant Generall, &amp;c, To the Right Worſhipfull Sir <hi>Thomas Glem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> Sarjeant Major Generall, my much honour'd Collonel, and to the reſt of the Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen, attending His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> Service in the City of <hi>Yorke.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable and Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>LOyalty</hi> as it is the Kings Joy, the Kingdomes Happineſſe, So the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Glory; So long then as your Hearts continue Loyall, your Names ſhall continue Glorious, being hereby a meanes to reſtore Joy to your King, and recover Happineſſe to the Kingdome. To you I Dedicate my Labours, That as they afford a Leſſon, So you a Patterne, both of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; whereby men may be the better moved either to yeeld the one their Practiſe, or the other their Imitation, Beſides <hi>(Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, and Right Worſhipfull)</hi> They who
<pb facs="tcp:30851:3"/>
take up Armes againſt the King, will not faile to take vp Armes againſt the Author, and Arguments too againſt his Worke. Your <hi>Patronage</hi> therefore muſt be my <hi>Refuge,</hi> and whilſt you are pleaſed to Protect my perſon, I feare not (by Gods Aſſiſtance) to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the Truth. Not in confidence of mine owne Ability's (for they are too weake) but becauſe (as Their Acclamation before <hi>Darius) Magna eſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritas</hi> &amp; <hi>Praevalecit:</hi> Great is Truth and it will Prevaile. You have Uouchſafed theſe Sermons your Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Pulpit, you have honoured them with your Command to the Preſſe; and now my requeſt is, that you will be Pleaſed to Countenance them with your Patronage to the Publique Veiw; In which I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent nothing is delivered, but what may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeme either the Tongue, or the Pen of a good Chriſtian, of a Loyall Subject, And of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant, <hi>R. MOSSOM.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>York, <date>Novemb. 20. 1642.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:30851:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>BEfore thou doſt peruſe the enſuing Diſcourſe, let me entreate thee to lay aſide all Prejudice, and with as much <hi>Sincerity</hi> to Reade, as the Author writ; and that is, ſo, is to enforme thy Judgement, not to pleaſe thy Fancy; to ſatisfie thy Conſ i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, not to ſtrengthen a Faction, making no better uſe of theſe Sermons, then <hi>Nero</hi> did of <hi>Seneca's</hi> Inſtructions, <hi>ad armandam malitiam,</hi> by perverting the Truth, to Arme thy Diſloyalty. Thou ſhalt finde here, That, endeavouring in ſome meaſure to doe well, I have followed the beſt, and kept my ſelfe to the Holy Scriptures, Ancient Fathers, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Divines (who I am ſure would teach me true Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) with which the Library in <hi>York</hi> (ſo uſefull and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary) did very well furniſh me. If then <hi>(Courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der)</hi> thou finde here the choiſeſt Flowers, (gathered out of the ſpacious Fields of larger Volumes) bound up into a fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grant Poſie of a ſhort Diſcourſe; Kiſſe the Hand that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents them in courteous Acceptance, defile it not with the Spittle of black-mouth'd Cenſure. If thou finde not things handled ſo fully as thou deſireſt, conſider the ſhort limits of an Houres Diſcourſe; if not ſo Learnedly as they might be, accept them as they are, and finde not fault till thou canſt do better, and then I ſhall be glad to be thy Reader; let me ſuffer, rather than Gods Truth, and in that, my Soveraognes Cauſe. There are ſome who quarrell at the Text, and will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve the Touchſtone naught, rather than acknowledge their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Counterfeit, but what is it thinkſt thou <hi>(Reader)</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Object? why, <hi>Solomon</hi> was a King, and ſpake in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> himſelfe. <hi>Odi profanum vulgus!</hi> the Objection
<pb facs="tcp:30851:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
will tell thee who are the Objectors, ſuch as will blaſpheme ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than be convinc't. But what more? Why, there is no riſing up againſt the King, as there is no riſing up againſt a Lyon, <hi>propter terrorem,</hi> leaſt he fall upon us, and rent us in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. But what? Is this the <hi>going well?</hi> Is this the <hi>come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in going,</hi> the Wiſeman ſpeaks of <hi>verſ. 29?</hi> no ſure. The beſt (if not all) Expoſitors Interpret this <hi>in bonam par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem;</hi> and if <hi>(Reader)</hi> thou doſt conſult the Commentators, and eſpecially <hi>Salazars</hi> Expoſition upon <hi>Solomons</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs, thou ſhalt be fully ſatisfyed. I will not conteſt about the Words of my Text (I can eaſily chuſe another) if ſo be, they will ſubſcribe to the Truth in my Sermons; with which, they who have not been convinc't, ſure I am, they have been ſilenc't. If in peruſing, thou turne Criticke (who like the Philomele is <hi>Vox &amp; praeterea nihil</hi>) conſider that theſe Sermons having had the Countenance of ſo great Nobles, ſo worthy Knights, and able Gentlemen; having had the Approbation of ſo learned Biſhops, ſo Reverend Doctors and other Divines, <hi>Quis tu?</hi> Who art thou, that I ſhould feare thy ſupercilious look, or malicious cenſure? I ſhall be glad if any Man more Able, will undertake the handling this Subject more fully. What I have done, if it may availe any thing (as ſomething I know it hath, and hope will more) to Gods Glory, in the Advancement of my Soveraigns Cauſe, I have my deſire. <hi>Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, whilſt thou art thy King's R. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:30851:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Sermon Preached in the Cathedrall Church in <hi>York,</hi> on the ſixth Day of <hi>November,</hi> 1642.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 30.31.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—And a King, againſt whom there is no ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up.</p>
                  <p>Let the Words of my mouth, and the Meditations of my Heart, be <hi>now and ever</hi> acceptable in thy ſight, O Lord my ſtrength and my Redeemer.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O frame a Diſcourſe, concerning the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of Kings, the Allegiance of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and the unlawfulneſſe of Rebellion; (after ſo many Learned Tongues and Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious Pens) is to make <hi>Iliads</hi> after <hi>Homer;</hi> to doe that, which hath been already ſo well done, that it cannot be done better. But fit it is the Preachers Trumpet ſhould ſound, ſo long as the Rebels Drum doth beate; fit it is to preſſe Loyalty to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, when the People are ſo much preſt to Diſloyalty. Who that they may know, they are not more willing, and able to defend the King, and His cauſe, by force of Armes, than the Scholler is, by force of Arguments. I have made choice of this Text, a fit Doctrine for theſe Times: <hi>And a King, againſt whom there is no riſing up.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Words.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of which Words, I will firſt ſpeak of their <hi>Dependance</hi> upon the former, implyed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:30851:5"/>
And; <hi>And a King, &amp;c.</hi> to underſtand this aright, we muſt look back to the 29. verſe, and ſo downewards. <hi>There be three things which goe well, yea foure which are comely in going: A Lyon which is ſtrongeſt amongſt beaſts, and turneth not away for any; a Grey-hound,</hi> or rather as the Margent, to which accords <hi>Junius, accinctus Lumbis Equus,</hi> an Horſe girt in the Loynes, <hi>Equus edoctus mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam,</hi> an Horſe trayned up for War; <hi>An He-Goate alſo, and a King, againſt whom, &amp;c.</hi> By the by, Obſerve; That the Scriptures are a rich Golden Mine, wherein, thoſe parts which ſeeme moſt earthy, have in them ſome rich Veines of Heavenly Doctrine. <hi>Solomon,</hi> not onely as a Man endued with Wiſedom (for then ſome would here, as in ſome paſſages elſe, have had the boldneſſe to have brought his Wiſedome into queſtion) but as a Man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired by the Holy Ghoſt, tells us here of things which goe well, and which are comely in going. But what is this to a godly Mans Inſtruction? Why, ſearch this oare, try it in the fire of diſcretion, and we ſhall extract ſome Golden Sentence, ſome Godly Doctrine. To omit the pious deſcant of <hi>Clarius</hi> the Scholiaſt, and others; I will adhere to that ſet rule of the Doctors of Lovaine. <hi>Quod quarto tribuitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Doctores Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanten. in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notat in loc.</note> 
               <hi>convenit etiam tribus; ſicut quod tribus adſcribitur, quarto convenit. That which is attributed to the fourth, is agreeable alſo to the three; as that which is aſcribed to the three, is agreeable alſo to the fourth.</hi> The Lyon then, the Horſe, and the he-Goate, are ſaid to goe well,<note place="margin">Vid. Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar. expoſit. in Proverb. Solomon.</note> and to be comely in going; <hi>ob innatam quandam Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtatem,</hi> for a certain innate Majeſty, which they eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally expreſſe in their manner of going. So that whereas the Wiſe Man ſaith, There are three things which goe well, yea, foure are comely in going; a Lyon, an Horſe, an he-Goate alſo, and a King; we may inſert this Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:30851:5"/>
               <hi>That Majeſty is the ornament of the Crown,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion inferd.</note> 
               <hi>the beauty and comelineſſe of a King.</hi> This for the <hi>Dependance.</hi> Now for the Words themſelves, <hi>A King againſt whom there is no riſing up.</hi> I will not divide the Words, for the King hath been too ill handled in Diviſions, I will therefore take them in order as they lye, and firſt ſpeak of the King; and for <hi>Method</hi> ſake,<note place="margin">The Method obſerved.</note> I will give you theſe Heads of my Diſcourſe. 1. <hi>Quid,</hi> what a King is. 2. <hi>Per quem,</hi> by Whom he is King.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quid,</hi> what the King is, <hi>in ſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>ad nos.</hi> 1. <hi>quid in ſe,</hi> what he is in himſelfe; and 2. <hi>quid ad nos,</hi> what he is to us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quid,</hi> what a King is? Some may here ſtop me,<note place="margin">Firſt <hi>Quid.</hi> What a King is.</note> 
               <hi>in limine,</hi> at the very Threſhold, and tell me, I may ſpare my paines, they know well enough what a King is. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they have ſome ſhew of Reaſon for't; for there have been too many <hi>Bethſhemites</hi> of late, who have curiouſly pry'd into <hi>Arcana Imperii,</hi> the Ark of Sacred Royalty. But ſtay; the matter is not ſo eaſie neither, to know what a King is; unleſſe what he is, muſt be reſolv'd, by what thoſe Men would have him be. All enjoy the benefit of the Sunnes glorious Light, and it's refreſhing Heate, but know not the quality of it's Celeſtiall Body, nor the greatneſſe of it's Heavenly Orbe. So all of us have, and (by Gods bleſſing) may enjoy the benefit of the Kings Government, and his Scepters Peace; yet know not the quality of his Kingly Office, nor the dignity of his Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Throne: Neither will I now determine either: onely ſuch Truths as are cleare in Scripture, evident in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, conſonant to Reaſon, and withall, agreeable to the Time. I will produce in the proſecution of this firſt particular, concerning the King: <hi>quid in ſe,</hi> what he is in himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:30851:6"/>
               <note place="margin">Firſt, <hi>quid in ſe,</hi> what he is in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Aquinas.</note>A King conſiſts eſpecially of theſe three; <hi>Huperoche, Exouſia,</hi> and <hi>'Arche. Huperoche,</hi> Excellency; <hi>Exouſia,</hi> Power; and <hi>'Arche,</hi> Principality; in which three, Kings of the Earth, are faire and glorious Reſemblances of the King of Heaven. <hi>Quicquid communiter de Deo &amp; Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turis dicitur, a Deo in Creaturas derivatur;</hi> Whatſoever is attributed in common to God and the Creature, is derived from God upon the Creature; ſo <hi>Aquinas</hi> upon <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. whereby, Kings are Gods Images, and glorious Beams of that all-glorious Sunne of Righteouſneſſe: Whence it is, that as God is often called King, ſo Kings often called Gods.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. <hi>Huperoche,</hi> Excellency, and that either <hi>Sanguinis,</hi> or <hi>Virtutis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Huperoche.</note> excellency of Birth, or excellency of Gifts: excellency of Birth, when <hi>Divus e ſanguine Divum,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended of the Blood Royall: excellency of Gifts, ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to diſcerne Judgement, and to goe in and out before his People.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cron.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. <hi>Exouſia,</hi> power, <hi>Civill and Eccleſiaſticall; Civill,</hi> over the Commonwealth; <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> over the Church.<note place="margin">Exouſia.</note> No power then above the King; not the Biſhop of Rome under the Goſpell, no more than the High Prieſt of the Jews under the Law, who had a Mitte upon his Head,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.6.</note> but withall, a Crown upon the Mitre. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. <hi>'Arche,</hi> principality or Government, being eſtabliſhed in his Throne,<note place="margin">Arche.</note> ſupreame Governour over all his people. <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroche,</hi> excellency, that for Direction; <hi>'Exouſia,</hi> power, that for execution; and <hi>'Arche,</hi> principality or Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſupported by both; for Excellency and Power are the two Leggs upon which Kings do ſtand, the two Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars upon which the Throne of Governement is eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Now theſe three things which compleat a King, require three things correſpondent to compleat a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject:<note place="margin">What a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</note> his <hi>Excellency,</hi> that requires <hi>Honour;</hi> his <hi>Power,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:30851:6"/>
Feare;</hi> his <hi>Principality, Obedience;</hi> and <hi>Excellency, Power; Principality,</hi> ther's a <hi>King; Honour, Feare; Obedience,</hi> ther's a Subject. But in that 1 of <hi>Timothy ch.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>Honour</hi> there is Gods Tribute, and belongs onely unto him: True, properly and exactly ſo it doth; but becauſe God hath imparted to the King of his <hi>Excellency,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo hath he imparted to him of his <hi>Honour, Pſal.</hi> 76. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Feare</hi> alſo, that is Gods Tribute, and belongs onely unto him: True, properly and exactly ſo it doth; but becauſe, <hi>Power is not but from above,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.11.</note> God imparting to Kings of the <hi>Power</hi> which he hath, imparts alſo unto them of the Feare we owe. So <hi>Obedience;</hi> alſo, God moſt peculiarly and exactly requires of us: yet we muſt be ſubject, we muſt be Obedient alſo to Kings, for the Lords ſake: he hath ordain'd their Government, and therefore enjoynes to them, as to himſelfe, our <hi>Obedience.</hi> If therefore <hi>Honour, Feare, Obedience,</hi> are the Kings dues,<note place="margin">Mat. 22.21.</note> then <hi>Apodoce,</hi> in the Language of our Saviour, <hi>reddite,</hi> render them, for ye cannot with-hold them, without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Injury; as to the King who hath this <hi>Excellency,</hi> this <hi>Power,</hi> this <hi>Principality,</hi> ſo alſo to him that gave it, even God himſelfe. Thus <hi>quid in ſe,</hi> what the King is in himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Quid ad nos,</hi> what he is to us. And he is firſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. quid ad nos,</hi> what he is to us.</note> 
               <hi>the Defendor of our Faith.</hi> Secondly, <hi>the preſerver of our Peace.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>the protector of our Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>The Defendor of our Faith,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor of our Faith. Iſaiah <hi>49.23</hi>
               </note> in the true Worſhip and Service of God; in which reſpect eſpecially, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſtiles Kings <hi>Nutricii Eccleſiae,</hi> the nurſing Fathers of the Church; to this purpoſe, as the Kings of the Jews had a Copy of the Law, ſo now our Kings the Book of holy Scriptures committed to them at their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auguration. That as the King of the Jews was <hi>Cuſtos
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:30851:7"/>
utriuſque Tabulae,</hi> the keeper of both the Tables; ſo ours alſo, <hi>Cuſtos utriuſque Teſtamenti,</hi> the keeper of both the Teſtaments.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">Secondly, the Preſerver of our Peace.</note>2. The <hi>Preſerver of our peace,</hi> preventing by his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or ſuppreſſing by his Power all Inſurrections at home; and withſtanding and repulſing all Invaſions from abroad.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 23.</note> Hence it is, that in the 34 of <hi>Ezech.</hi> the King is called, <hi>the Shepheard of his people;</hi> the Shepheard, as <hi>paſcere</hi> to Feed them, <hi>regere,</hi> to Guide them, ſo <hi>tueri</hi> too, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them, to defend one from the other, and all from the Wolfe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 20.</note> one from another, the Leane from the Fat, the poore from his Oppreſſor, and all from the Wolfe; the Wolfe, the Enemy without the Fold, the Enemy without the Kingdome. In that 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.2. we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>pray, for Kings,</hi> Why? that we may live <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remon kai 'Eſuchion Bion,</hi> a peaceable and quiet Life; <hi>Heremon Bion,</hi> a peaceable Life, free from Civill Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions, and <hi>'Eſuchion</hi> too, <hi>a quiet Life,</hi> ſafe from For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Invaſions. This then is the King alſo <hi>ad nos,</hi> to us, the <hi>preſerver of our peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. The <hi>Protector of our Laws,</hi> as the Sunne is the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Light,<note place="margin">The prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of our Laws.</note> ſo the King the Fountaine of Juſtice; the Magiſtrates in the State, like the Starres in the Heavens: the Starres borrow their luſtre of Light from the Sunne, and the Magiſtrates their power of Juſtice from the King; the Rule of which Juſtice are the Laws. So that if any Magiſtrates ſhall violate the Laws, they eclipſe the Kings Juſtice, and caſt diſhonour upon his Throne. Which Indignity to revenge, he hath the Sword com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him by God, and is appointed <hi>Vindex malo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4.</note> to take vengeance on them that do evill, and this <hi>protection of our Laws,</hi> is the <hi>preſervation of our peace,</hi> and <hi>defence of Religion,</hi> the glory of both. This then is the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:30851:7"/>
King <hi>ad nos,</hi> to us, the <hi>Defendor of the Faith,</hi> and to that end eſpecially he hath <hi>Huperochen,</hi> his <hi>Excellency;</hi> the <hi>preſerver of our peace,</hi> and to that end eſpecially he hath <hi>'Exouſian,</hi> Power; the <hi>Protector of our Laws,</hi> and to that end eſpecially he hath <hi>'Archen,</hi> Principality, or Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; or, put them altogether, as in good Kings they are ne're aſunder, he hath <hi>Excellency, Power, Principality;</hi> for the <hi>Defence of the Faith,</hi> the <hi>preſervation of the Peace,</hi> and the <hi>protection of the Laws of his Kingdom.</hi> That the King is <hi>in ſe,</hi> in himſelfe; this he is <hi>ad nos,</hi> to us. Now on our part is due to the King, a <hi>full maintenance of his Royall Eſtate;</hi> a <hi>full Maintenance</hi> is due, <hi>non donum ſed debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> not a Gift, but a Debt, <hi>For this cauſe pay you Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute alſo,</hi> ſo Saint <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13.6. from which Tribute,<note place="margin">Aquinas Comment. in Rom. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> though <hi>Aquinas</hi> will have the Clergy exempted <hi>ex pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilegio Principum,</hi> by the priviledge granted them from Princes (for indeed, no Man can remit a Debt, but he to whom the debt is owing) yet he confeſſeth, it hath, <hi>equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem quidem Naturalem,</hi> truely a Naturall Equity; for it is Equity indeed, if we will have <hi>our Faith defended, our Peace preſerved,</hi> and <hi>our Laws protected,</hi> that then the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency, Power and Principality of the King</hi> ſhould be maintained. To ſee a Man ſtand bare headed, we account an ordinary and uſuall Signe of <hi>Subjection;</hi> and what is it think we then, to ſee a State bare headed? the Prince who is the head kept bare, not onely denuded of his power and Aurhority, but alſo of his meanes and maintenance?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> But what is the Subject excluded? may not he ſtand up in the <hi>defence of the Faith,</hi> the <hi>preſervation of the peace,</hi> and the <hi>protection of the Laws?</hi> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſ."/> Yes, riſe up he may, but with his King, not againſt him; for <hi>againſt him there is no riſing up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> But what if the King neglects? nay, ſeduced by his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:30851:8"/>
evill Councellors oppoſeth, the ſincerity and truth of Religion? may not the Subject then ſtand upon Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons guard, and Defend the Faith, even againſt the King himſelfe? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſ."/>
               <note place="margin">Judg. <hi>6.</hi> v. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> Here I might anſwer as <hi>Joaſh</hi> did, <hi>Let Baal pleade for himſelfe,</hi> let wicked Kings Patronize their owne Cauſe; Thanks be to God, we have no cauſe to complaine of our Kings wickedneſſe, but of our own; and ſo need not I pleade for evill Kings, ſince God hath given us ſo good and gracious a King. But becauſe this is that which many pretend, to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance their unlawfull Armes; I Anſwer, That in caſe a King neglects, nay, ſeduced by evill Councellors oppoſeth the ſincerity and truth of Religion: the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects may not riſe up againſt the King, <hi>Vi &amp; Armis,</hi> with Force and Arms; but <hi>Precibus &amp; Lachrymis,</hi> with Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Teares, the Weapons with which the ancient Chriſtians overcame the cruelty of their Perſecutors; according to that of Saint <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard Epiſt. <hi>221.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Stabimas &amp; pugna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>himus uſque ad mortem (ſi ita oportuerit,)</hi> We will ſtand to it, and fight even unto Death, (if need be,) But how? why, heare the Father, <hi>non ſcutis &amp; Gladiis,</hi> not with Shields and Swords, <hi>ſed precibus &amp; fletibus ad Deum,</hi> with Prayers and Teares unto God.</p>
            <p>The Subject then may defend, by Petition to the King, and Prayers for the King. By Petition, I ſay, to the King, yet not as <hi>Caeſars</hi> Captaine Petitioned the Roman Senate (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> Relates it) with his Hand upon the Pummell of his Sword; that if they would not grant it, that ſhould give it. And in caſe the <hi>King</hi> will not Grant, not Reade, not Receive a Petition, then <hi>Vince ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendo,</hi> ouercome by ſuffering. And if it be the Truth of the Goſpell a Man ſtands for, ſo that the goodneſſe of the Cauſe will beare him out, he muſt not refuſe to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:30851:8"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> goe Death it ſelfe, and ſo obtaine a Crowne of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to be a Martyr himſelfe by Chriſtian Patience; not Martyr the State by Civill diſſentions. King <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> was choſen by God to build the Temple, becauſe he was <hi>a King of Peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cron.</hi> 2.</note> Sure then <hi>(Beloved)</hi> whatſoever Men may pretend, God hath not choſen them to reforme the Church, who are Men of War, yea, War againſt their King, againſt a <hi>Solomon</hi> too, War againſt <hi>a King of Peace.</hi> To raiſe a Civill War is certainely to exalt Satans Kingdome, and not Gods or the King; every where (as too ſad experience tells us) to ſettle vile Profanation, no where to ſettle true Religion.</p>
            <p>And if Petitions to the King will not prevaile, we muſt uſe Prayers to God, for <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>The Kings heart is in the hand of the Lord</hi> (not in the power of the People) <hi>and he turneth it whetherſoever he will.</hi> He can move evill Princes to good, in mercy to his People, as he did <hi>Belſhazzar</hi> and <hi>Darius,</hi> as well as ſuffer good Princes to be moved to evill, in judgement to his People, as he did <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Hezekiah;</hi> yea, as he can move evill Princes, ſo remove them at his pleaſure, as he did <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ahab.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the full clearing of this, belongs to the laſt part of the Text. Onely this by the way; Since there are Men, who are now up in Arms againſt their gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne; leaſt any ſhould be led away with their faire pretences, we muſt know, That no Man ought to take up Armes, but in the Defence of a juſt cauſe,<note place="margin">Note.</note> and in Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to a lawfull Command. For, as a Man muſt have a good Cauſe to juſtifie his Arms, ſo a lawfull Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to juſtifie his Cauſe: which who ſo wants, is not onely a Rebell, but a Murderer, as <hi>Bernard</hi> to the Templars, <hi>Serm.</hi> 1. Concerning unlawfull Duels, ſo may I ſay of him who takes up unlawfull Arms, if he dyes, <hi>Moritur ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micida,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:30851:9"/>
he dyes a Murderer; if he lives, <hi>Vivit homicida,</hi> he lives a Murderer: yea, whether he lives or dyes, <hi>Eſt homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cida,</hi> he is a Murderer: <hi>Occ ſor lethaliter peccat, &amp; occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus aeternaliter perit;</hi> if he lives, he is ſpiritually dead in that he ſlew, and if he dyes, he is eternally dead in that he is ſlaine, ſlaine without Repentance: here then enter a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Deliberation, and no ſudden Reſolution. Were the Cauſe as Juſt as is pretended, though no Man will think, to pillage Houſes the way to reforme the State, to deface Churches the way to confirme Religion; formerly tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Bell on the Lords Day, hath been accounted a great breach of the Sabbath; now, ſounding of Trumpets, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Drums, taking of Caſtles, plundering of Houſes on the Lords Day, an acceptable and commendable Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Will any Man think this the way of <hi>Reformation?</hi> no ſure, unleſſe this <hi>Reformation</hi> muſt be another <hi>Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and ſo require another <hi>Chaos of Confuſion.</hi> But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe we yet the Cauſe as good (I ſay) as is pretended; yet where is the lawfull Command of <hi>Authority?</hi> As for <hi>Excellency, Power,</hi> and <hi>Principallity,</hi> which muſt conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute this <hi>Authority:</hi> The <hi>Scriptures</hi> allowes them to Kings, denyes them to Subjects, though Magiſtrates, yea, the higheſt Magiſtrates, denyes them (I ſay) joyntly and together as in Kings. For the Magiſtrate though ne're ſo high,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.14.</note> he is the <hi>Kings Creature.</hi> So Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and ſo his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Governement</hi> a Derivative. The Subject may have an <hi>Huperochen,</hi> an <hi>Excellency of Gifts;</hi> yea, <hi>Megiſten Huperochen,</hi> the greateſt <hi>Excellency,</hi> which makes him ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of being Councellor to the King, but not a King. But his <hi>'Exouſia</hi> and <hi>'Arche,</hi> his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Governement,</hi> being only Delegate, and Derived from the King; it is not Conſonant to Reaſon, that they ſhould afford a lawfull Command againſt the King. For the King being the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:30851:9"/>
Fountaine from whence the Magiſtrates <hi>Power</hi> doth Streame; how againſt Nature is it, for the Streame to run backwards into the Fountain? for the <hi>Power</hi> derived from the King, to be exerciſed againſt the King? So that whil'ſt Men take up Armes and proſecute a Civill War againſt the King, in ſtead of <hi>Defending,</hi> we ſee, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Religion, in ſtead of <hi>Preſerving;</hi> they diſturbe the Peace, in ſtead of <hi>Protecting;</hi> they violate the Laws, and that in an high Meaſure, and an hainous Nature. Indeed if we aske, whether there be any <hi>Cauſe</hi> that can juſtifie <hi>Armes</hi> againſt the King, and any <hi>Authority</hi> that can ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the <hi>Cauſe?</hi> The <hi>Scriptures</hi> (as ſhall afterwards ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare) will ſay no, the Fathers ſay no, the beſt of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Divines ſay no. What ſhall we ſay then? or rather, what ſhall we doe then? Why, <hi>Defend</hi> our Kings Perſon, and he will <hi>Defend</hi> our Religion; <hi>Preſerve</hi> His Honour, and he will preſerve our <hi>Peace;</hi> maintaine His <hi>Royalty,</hi> and He will protect our <hi>Lawes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Strigellus</hi> tells us, That <hi>Alphonſus</hi> King of <hi>Naples,</hi> his Embleme was, <hi>A Pelican feeding her young with her own Blood;</hi> with this Motto, (better applyed then of late) <hi>Pro Rege &amp; pro Grege.</hi> What was that Kings, may be moſt truely Ours; who Pelican like, is now ready to ſpend His owne Blood, for the redeeming His owne Honour, and His Peoples ſafety; and if ye now tread in His ſteps, follow His Example, in being ready to ſacrifice your own Lives, for the Honour of your King, and the Peace of your Country, if ye dye in the enterpriſe, your Deathes ſhall not be <hi>Mortes,</hi> but <hi>Immortalitates,</hi> having made your peace with God, an Eternall Reward ſhall attend your Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Deaths. And here I paſſe from <hi>Quid,</hi> What the King is, to the <hi>per Quem,</hi> by whom he is King.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Perquem,</hi> by whom he King.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Per Quem,</hi> by whom? If we come to <hi>Solomons Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs,</hi> we ſhall finde this <hi>per quem</hi> anſwered, with a <hi>per
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:30851:10"/>
Me,</hi> Prov. 8.15. <hi>per Me Reges Regnant,</hi> by me Kings Reigne, by Me King of Kings, and Lord of Lords: where the <hi>per</hi> is not a meere Permiſſion, but a full Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; it is not that they Reigne by my Sufferance, but by mine Ordinance, for if we bring our <hi>per quem</hi> to St. <hi>Paul,</hi> he will anſwer us with an <hi>Ordinatae ſunt a Deo:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>The Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers which are, are ordained of God.</hi> Bring this <hi>per quem</hi> to the Ancient Fathers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> will tell us, That <hi>Cujus juſſu homines naſcuntur, hujus juſſu &amp; Reges conſtituuntur:</hi> By whoſe Command Men are Created, by his Command are Kings Ordained. <hi>Tertullian in Apologet.</hi> tells us, <hi>Inde eſt Imperator, unde &amp; homo antiquam Imperator,</hi> By him is the Emperour, by whom he is Man before he be Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <hi>Inde poteſtas illi, unde &amp; Spiritus,</hi> from him he hath his Power, from whom he hath his Spirit. Hence it is, that in 1 <hi>Cron. c.</hi> 29. <hi>v.</hi> 23. it is ſaid, Solomon <hi>ſate on the Throne of the Lord, in ſolium Domini,</hi> not <hi>in ſolium Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puli, on the Throne of the Lord, not on the Throne of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Yea, bring this <hi>per quem</hi> to the Heathen, and ſuch is the dictate of Nature, that he will anſwer it with a <hi>per Jovem.</hi> And it were more than a Miracle, that among the Heathen (as one hath well obſerv'd) ſo many Princes ſhould ſubmit themſelves to one, and that one peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a Woman, peradventure a Childe; were it not that they did acknowledge a Divine Power (which St. <hi>Paul</hi> more Divine-like, calls <hi>Gods Ordinance</hi>) which begat a Reverence in their hearts. Hence it is that we owe Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Subjection unto Kings (though wicked) even becauſe of <hi>Gods Ordinance;</hi> for as the unfaithfulneſſe of a Man cannot fruſtrate <hi>Gods promiſe,</hi> as appears, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. ſo nor can the Wickedneſſe of the Perſon make void <hi>Gods Ordinance:</hi> So that a King is nor a King, becauſe he is a good King, nor leaves being a King, when he leaves being
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:30851:10"/>
good. We give Honour, ſaith Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> well, not <hi>proſwpw,</hi> but <hi>proſwpwpoiw,</hi> not to Man: but to God in Man. So that as contempt of the Magiſtrate the <hi>Kings</hi> Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, is contempt of the King, who ordained the Magiſtrate; ſo contempt of the King, Gods Vicegerent, is contempt of God who ordained the King. For in the chain of order one linke ſtill depends upon the other. Saint <hi>Baſils</hi> advice then is good, That we give Honour, <hi>Tois men calois hws tw thew, tois de cacois dia ton theon,</hi> to godly <hi>Kings,</hi> as to God; to wicked <hi>Kings</hi> for God. Though <hi>Kings</hi> themſelves then be evill, yet muſt we reverence Gods Ordinance, and not reſiſt, but ſuffer their Commands to be fulfilled, either <hi>a nobis,</hi> or <hi>de nobis; a nobis,</hi> in Active obedience, if lawfull; <hi>de nobis,</hi> in Paſſive, if unlawfull, we muſt take up, not a Sword of reſiſtance, but a Buckler of patience; and if occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion be, we muſt maintaine Truth and Juſtice <hi>morte,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>marte,</hi> by ſuffering rather than by reſiſting. For <hi>qui inſurgit in Chriſtum Domini, inſurgit in Dominum Chriſti,</hi> He that riſeth up againſt the Anoynted of the Lord, riſeth up againſt the Lord of the Anoynted. <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chomachoi,</hi> are <hi>theomachoi,</hi> fighters againſt the <hi>Kings,</hi> are fighters againſt God. Therefore howſoever we reſpect the Royall Perſon as Man, we muſt <hi>Honour, Feare, and Obey</hi> him as <hi>King.</hi> For therefore are <hi>Kings</hi> called Gods, as <hi>Bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> well, upon <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. <hi>non quod natura ſint Dii, ſed quod officium eorum ordinatio ſit divina:</hi> Not becauſe they are Gods by Nature, but becauſe their <hi>Kingly Office,</hi> is Gods Divine Ordinance. Since the <hi>King</hi> then is <hi>per Deum,</hi> by God, we muſt <hi>Honour, Feare, and Obey</hi> him <hi>propter Deum,</hi> for God, which is the Charecter of a good Chriſtian, as well as a good Subject; who doth <hi>arceſſere rivum fidelitatis, a fonte pietatis,</hi> draw the ſtreame of Loyalty from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Piety; and where Loyalty is the Daughter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, like <hi>Naomi</hi> and <hi>Ruth,</hi> they are inſeparable. When
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:30851:11"/>
               <hi>Saul</hi> was made <hi>King,</hi> though the Sonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> did deſpiſe him, yet, <hi>they whoſe hearts God had touched</hi> (ſay the Scriptures, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10.26.) <hi>they followed after him.</hi> They did not then look upon him as the Son of <hi>Kiſh,</hi> but as the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> as after, <hi>David</hi> looked upon him, not as his Perſecutor, but as his Soveraigne; and therefore though cruell and impious, yet did he Honour him, <hi>propter Deum,</hi> as the Lords Anoynted. And thus have I done with the firſt word, <hi>Rex,</hi> a <hi>King;</hi> having ſhown you, 1 <hi>Quid,</hi> what a <hi>King</hi> is. 2. <hi>Per quem,</hi> by whom he is <hi>King. Quid in ſe,</hi> what a <hi>King</hi> is in himſelfe, <hi>Huperoche, 'Exouſia, &amp; 'Arche,</hi> Excellency, Power, and Principality; which require of us, <hi>Honour, Feare,</hi> and <hi>Obedience. Quid ad nos,</hi> what he is to us, the <hi>defender of our Faith,</hi> the <hi>preſerver of our Peace,</hi> and the <hi>protector of our Laws;</hi> which require of us a full main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of his Royall Eſtate. This for the <hi>quid.</hi> 2. The <hi>per quem,</hi> anſwered with a <hi>per me,</hi> where <hi>non vox hominum ſonat,</hi> it is not the voyce of Man, but of God, by him <hi>Kings</hi> Reigne, who <hi>looſeth the bond of Kings, and guirdeth their loynes with a girdle, Job.</hi> 12.18. This the Summe of what hath been delivered. I ſhould now ſpeak of that which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, <hi>againſt whom there is no riſing up.</hi> But of theſe Words, when opportunity ſhall be offered. Give me leave to adde a word or two, which ſhall neither be <hi>propter,</hi> nor <hi>ultra tempus,</hi> beſide, or beyond the Time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beloved, Elijahs</hi> ſmall Cloud hath now overſpread the whole face of the Heavens with a Storme; The not long ſince Tumults, have overſpread the whole Kingdom with a Civill War, and we muſt now know, Stormes come not but by Vapors, ſo that if the Storme of Gods Judgements fall down upon us, the Vapours of our filthy Sinnes have firſt aſcended: take away the Vapors, the Storme will ceaſe; take away our Sinnes, Gods Judgements will be
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:30851:11"/>
removed. We attribute the continuance and encreaſe of our miſeries, to the raging malice of the Adverſary; who like <hi>Jehu, drives furiou ly,</hi> and what conditions of peace are offered, yea, what Articles concluded, he caſts them behinde his back. But indeed we ought to look within our ſelves, and if we deſire peace with Men, we muſt firſt make our peace with God, and having made our peace with him, we need not feare the Enmity of Man. God ſhall be to us, what he was to <hi>David,</hi> Pſ. 62. <hi>our Rocke, and our Salvation, our Defence, our Refuge, and our Glory.</hi> And if he be our <hi>Rock,</hi> what Storme ſhall ſhake us? if our <hi>Salvation,</hi> what trouble ſhall deject us? if our <hi>Defence,</hi> what Weapon ſhal Wound us? if our <hi>Refuge,</hi> what Enemy ſhall purſue us? if our <hi>Glory,</hi> what Tongue ſhall diſgrace us? Feare we not then the power or violence of the Adverſary, feare we not his great ſtrength. It is a remarkeable paſſage, which Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory relates concerning <hi>Phocas,</hi> who when he had ſlaine his Maſter the Emperour <hi>Mauritius,</hi> he ſtrengthened him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe with ſtrong forces, fortified himſelf about with ſtrong Walls; and when he thought himſelfe ſecure from the Enemy without, he heard a voyce in the Night ſaying to him, <hi>The Enemy that is within, that ſhall deſtroy thee,</hi> meaning his rebellious ſin; the Application is eaſie. We may (bleſſed be God) ſay with holy <hi>David,</hi> Pſ. 21.2. <hi>In virtute tua Domine, The King ſhall rejoyce in thy ſtrength, O Lord, exceeding glad ſhall he be of thy Salvation.</hi> The <hi>King</hi> ſhall rejoyce in thy Strength, not in the ſtrength and number of his people, not in the valour and proweſſe of his Captains; but <hi>Virtute tua Domine,</hi> in the might of the Almighty, for that is <hi>Virtus ad Salutem;</hi> that <hi>Strength</hi> brings <hi>Salvation;</hi> in which <hi>Salvation</hi> great ſhall be our <hi>Kings Joy,</hi> great ſhall be his <hi>Glory</hi> and his <hi>Honours, v.</hi> 5. Now <hi>Regis ad exemplum,</hi> let not us place our Strength in an Arme of Fleſh, which like <hi>Jeroboams</hi> hand ſhall ſuddenly wither, and bring ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitable
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:30851:12"/>
ruine upon us: but let us rely upon the Arms of the Almighty, which are <hi>Everlaſting,</hi> Deut. 33.27. ſtrecht out to all Eternity, as for the Defence of his Anoynted, ſo for the Safety of all thoſe, who repoſe their whole truſt and Confidence in him.</p>
            <p>Let others thinke Force of Arms whereby they offend God no leſſe than their King, the way to reforme and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire all: my advice to you is, that if you deſire the Times ſhould mend, you would firſt mend your ſelves; and to that end, in unfaigned humiliation betake your ſelves to God with Prayers and Tears, leaſt your Darkeneſſe be without Light, your Judgement without any Beams of Mercy. Sue to God for a Treaty of Peace (for your Soules firſt, and then for the Kingdom) ſending forth, <hi>Legationem Lachrymarum,</hi> (as <hi>Gregory</hi> calls the weeping of a Penitent) an Embaſſage of Teares, to which God will aſſuredly give a gracious au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Now that our State like <hi>Noahs</hi> Ark is toſſed upon the waters of Civil Diſſentions, ſend out the Dove of hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prayer, and though it return into your boſomes, as the Dove into the Ark, empty; yet ſend it out again, and at length it wil bring in the Olive Branch of Peace. Though the fury of War had ſuckt out all the marrow of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, ſo that it were like thoſe dry bones in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets viſion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 37. <hi>v.</hi> 4.5.6.</note> yet by our Prayers and Tears we ſhould ſo prevaile with God, that (according to the Scirptures expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) he would make the ſeverall Joynts of Kings, Nobles, and People, to knit again; and tye them together with their Sinnes and Ligaments, Loyalty and affection; cloathe them with their old Fleſh, of peace and plenty; wrap them in their old skin of Riches and Glory, and breath Life into them again, even the execution of juſtice, the life of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and ſoule of a Kingdom; which God of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy, and for <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> his all-ſufficient Merits gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly vouchſafe unto us, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:30851:12"/>
            <head>To His Excellency WILLIAM EARLE of NEWCASTLE, Generall of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Forces in the North, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not the Excellency of the Work, which hath induced me, to preſent it to the Patronage of your <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency;</hi> But becauſe there is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, or rather a Combination of Men, who with <hi>Hermogenes</hi> in <hi>Tertullian, Maledicere ſingulis officium bonae Conſcientiae judicant,</hi> think it the diſcharge of a good Conſcience, to ſpeak evill (yea and to doe evill) againſt all thoſe who oppoſe them: The ſame dutifull reſpect, which begot the intention of having your <hi>Excellency</hi> my Auditor, begot alſo the deſire of obtaining you my Protector; that as the Worke hath had the Grace of ſo generall an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, ſo the Author the Countenance of ſo Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable a Patronage, and withall the Protection of ſo Worthy an Excellency. The prayſes of whoſe greateſt Worth, are beſt heard from the Voyce of this greateſt County; into which (by the ſolicita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:30851:13"/>
of the Loyall Nobility and Gentry, and by Commiſſion from His Sacred Majeſty) your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency hath advanced with your preſent Forces, to repreſſe the fury of Rebellion; which, neither pittying the tenderneſſe of Infancy, nor the infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of old Age; neither regarding the Priviledge of Sex, nor the plea of Condition, hath offered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humane violence to all. And now (Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) maugre the malicious attempts of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious (whatſoever is the iſſue of your noble En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours) here ſhall Poſterity finde it Recorded, That <hi>William</hi> Earle of Newcaſtle was Loyall to His Soveraigne, and faithfull to his Country; <hi>Quem non Ardor prava jubentium mente qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit ſolidâ.</hi> Whoſe Memory ſhall be precious in the minds of all good Men, and Loyall Subjects. So that, ſhould you Sacrifice your Selfe in affection to your King and Country; your Honourable Death ſhall be a means to procure you a Glorious Life, and an Eternity of Happineſſe ſhall Crown your Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity to your Prince. In whoſe Honour and Safety, that you may be preſerv'd ſafe and Honourable, is the devout Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Excellency's moſt humbly devoted Servant. R. MOSSOM.</signed>
               <dateline>York, <date>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the fifth, <hi>1642</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:30851:13"/>
            <head>The Second Sermon Preached in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Church in <hi>York,</hi> on the 27. of <hi>November,</hi> 1642.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov. 30.31.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>—And a King, againſt whom there is no ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up.</p>
                  <p>Let the words of my mouth, and the Meditations of my Heart, be <hi>now and ever</hi> acceptable in thy ſight, O Lord my ſtrength and my Redeemer.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AN abrupt Beginning dulls the Attention of the Auditor; for the better Introduction then to our preſent Diſcourſe; give me leave to recapitulate, and recall to your Memories, the Heads of our former. In the handling of the Words, I ſhewed you firſt their <hi>Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance,</hi> implyed in the Conjunction <hi>And; And a King:</hi> From whence I infer'd this <hi>Concluſion,</hi> That Majeſty is the Ornament of the Crown, the beauty and comelineſſe of a King. The Words themſelves I took in order as they lye, making a King the Subject, yet without ſubjecting the King; for our method was, Firſt to ſhew you <hi>quid,</hi> What a King is. 2. <hi>Per quem,</hi> by whom he is King, &amp;c. Here I left the King, in his Relation to His Subjects; and Here I left the Subjects, in their Relation to their King. And I wiſh this mutuall Relation had been kept ſo invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate, as that, having ſpoken of the King, I had not any
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:30851:14"/>
occaſion to enter upon the latter Words of my Text, more than to repeate the Words themſelves, and tell you that, <hi>againſt him there is no riſing up.</hi> But ſince <hi>Solomons Nemo inſurgit,</hi> there is no riſing up, is turn'd into <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids, multi inſurgunt,</hi> many are they that riſe up. I could not any longer ſit ſtill, but riſe up I muſt too (and good manners you will ſay when my betters riſe before me) But how riſe up? why, as every good Subject ought to doe <hi>pro,</hi> not <hi>con,</hi> for the King not againſt him: For, <hi>againſt him there is no riſing up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the handling of which Words, I ſhall obſerve this Method.<note place="margin">The Method</note> 1. To ſpeak of the Words as denying <hi>rem factam</hi> the thing done; and herein I follow <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melius</hi> with their <hi>in quem nemo inſurgit,</hi> the ſame with our Engliſh, <hi>Againſt whom there is no riſing up.</hi> 2. As denying, <hi>jus facti,</hi> the lawfulneſſe of doing the thing; herein I follow <hi>Lyranus, Clarius</hi> the Scholiaſt, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of <hi>Lovaine,</hi> and others, with their <hi>nec eſt qui reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtat ei,</hi> neither is there any that may reſiſt him. Having done with the Words as denying <hi>rem factam,</hi> the thing done, and <hi>jus facti,</hi> the lawfulneſſe of doing the thing. I ſhall ſhew you the <hi>quomodo,</hi> and the <hi>quare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>quomodo,</hi> the <hi>manner</hi> how, <hi>there is no riſing up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>quare,</hi> the <hi>reaſon,</hi> why <hi>there is no riſing up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>quomodo</hi> the <hi>manner,</hi> how <hi>there is no riſing up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Non Corde,</hi> no riſing up in the <hi>Heart, malum cogitando,</hi> in thinking evill. 2. <hi>Non Lingua,</hi> no riſing up with the <hi>Tongue, maledicendo,</hi> in ſpeaking evill. 3. <hi>Non Manu,</hi> no riſing up with the <hi>Hand, malefaciendo,</hi> in doing evill.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>quare,</hi> the <hi>reaſon,</hi> why <hi>there is no riſing up,</hi> and that is, 1. <hi>Propter malum culpae,</hi> for the evill of ſinne. 2. <hi>Propter malum paenae,</hi> for the evill of puniſhment, Rebellion being properly Satans ſin, both to denotate the <hi>krima,</hi> and the <hi>katakrima,</hi> the guilt and the puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:30851:14"/>1. Then to ſpeak of the Words as denying <hi>rem factam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Denying <hi>rem factam</hi> the thing done.</note> the thing done, <hi>in quem nemo inſurgit,</hi> ſo <hi>Junius, againſt whom there is no riſing up,</hi> ſo our Engliſh. But what? <hi>Nemo inſurgit,</hi> no riſing up? What meaneth then thoſe ſoundings of Trumpets, thoſe beatings of Drums, thoſe Alarums of War? Are theſe ſo frequent in our Ears, and yet <hi>Nemo inſurgit,</hi> no riſing up? What think you? was <hi>Solomon</hi> acquainted with the Logick of our Times, that Towns ſhould be Garriſon'd, Armies raiſ'd, Fields pitcht, Battails fought, contrary to the Kings Command, with contempt of the Kings Majeſty, and with hazard of the Kings Life, and yet <hi>Nemo inſurgit,</hi> no riſing up againſt the King? no ſure; there is <hi>ingens hiatus,</hi> a vaſt diſtance betwixt <hi>Achitophels</hi> policy, and <hi>Solomons</hi> Wiſedome; that foments Diſloyalty and Faction, this inſtructs Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Subjection. What then? is it, becauſe ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up in Rebellion againſt the King, is a Sin ſo horrible, and the Miſeries which attend this Sin ſo inſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that <hi>Negare maluit quam prohibere,</hi> he rather choſe to deny than to forbid it? That as St. <hi>Paul, Epheſ.</hi> 5.3. <hi>would not have covetouſneſſe ſo much as once named amongſt the Saints,</hi> ſo nor <hi>Solomon</hi> here Rebellion amongſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects? This doubtleſſe is not far from the Wiſe-Mans intent. But the truth is, <hi>non tam negat, quam negando fortius prohibet,</hi> he doth not ſo abſolutely deny, as by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the more ſtrongly forbid. For we may obſerve, that in the Language of the Scriptures, as the ſtrongeſt <hi>Negation</hi> is by an <hi>Interrogative,</hi> ſo the ſtrongeſt <hi>prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> is by a <hi>Negative:</hi> as here, <hi>Rex in quem nemo inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git; A King againſt whom there is no riſing up.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Denying <hi>jus facti.</hi> the lawfulneſſe of doing the thing.</note> Thus as denying <hi>rem factam,</hi> the thing done.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As denying <hi>jus facti,</hi> the lawfulneſſe of doing the thing. And here I muſt lanch out into the deep, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:30851:15"/>
not fearing what Stormes may follow, ſteare forwards; guiding my Courſe by the Compaſſe of Gods Word. <hi>Non eſt qui reſiſtat ei,</hi> ſo <hi>Clarius</hi> the Scholiaſt, and others, <hi>Neither is there any that may reſiſt him.</hi> Not any, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Clergy or Laity, whether Private Perſons or Publique, whether Lords or Commons. <hi>Solomon</hi> hath a <hi>Non eſt qui reſiſtat ei</hi> for them all. <hi>Let every Soule be ſubject to the higher Powers,</hi> ſo Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 13.1. <hi>paſa pſuche</hi> every Soule, <hi>ſi quis tentat excipere conatur decipere,</hi> is the known Language of S. <hi>Bernard,</hi> he that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to except, endeavours to deceive. Though a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet then, an Apoſtle, or Evangeliſt, though a Man of an Extraordinary Calling, yet ſubject to the Ordinary Juriſdiction; no Cloyſter or Church, no Profeſſion, Employment or Dignity, is a Sanctuary, a Priviledg'd Place, from the Tribute of Obedience due to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> To apprehend the ſtrict tye, in which the Subject is bound to His Soveraigne; we muſt know that Kings, are the Succeſſors of the Patriarches, both in the right of their Fatherhood, as Fathers of the Country; and in the rule of their Government as Governours of the Commonwealth. The difference ſeems to be only this, that the Patriarchs were Kings of their Families, and Kings are the Fathers of their Countries.<note place="margin">B. Andrews.</note> So that <hi>jus Regium</hi> commeth out of <hi>jus Patrium,</hi> the Kings right from the Fathers, and both hold by one Commandement morall, and one Bond naturall; ſo that as the Sonne by the ſame Command of God is bound to obey his Father, that the Subject is to obey His King; So by the ſame Bond of Nature the Subject is to obey his King, that the Sonne is to obey his Father.<note place="margin">What the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of a Subject to his King.</note> Yea, in the Relation of a Subject to His King, is contain'd not onely the Relation of a Sonne to his Father, but alſo of a Wife to her Husband, of a Servant
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:30851:15"/>
to his Maſter. And what Father will admit it lawfull, for his Sonne violently to reſiſt him? What Huſband, for his Wife forcibly to oppoſe him? What Maſter, for his Servant to riſe up againſt him? And ſhall we admit it lawfull then, for the Subject violently to reſiſt, forcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to oppoſe, and with Arms to riſe up againſt the King, who is <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> the Father of the Country; <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Reipublicae,</hi> the Huſband of the Commonwealth, and <hi>Subditorum Dominus,</hi> the Lord of all His Subjects? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> True (may ſome ſay) it is impious indeed to reſiſt a King that is pious; but a King by impiety doth <hi>degenerare in Tyrannum,</hi> degenerate and become a Tyrant; and when the King deſerts his Duty, no marvaile if the Subjects forſake their Loyalty.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſ."/> As if Kings received their Crowns, as ſome high Officers their Commiſſions with a <hi>dum bene ſe geſſerint.</hi> I told you before, and now tell you againe. I might here anſwer as <hi>Joaſh</hi> did, <hi>Judg.</hi> 6. <hi>Let Baal pleade for himſelfe,</hi> let wicked Kings Patronize their own cauſe (thanks be to God) we have no cauſe to complaine of our Kings wickedneſſe, but of our own, and ſo need not I pleade for evill Kings, ſince God hath beſtowed upon us ſo good and gracious a King, had we but thankfull Hearts to acknowledge his Goodneſſe. Yet becauſe the Preſſe and the Pulpit have abounded with falſe aſperſions caſt upon the Royall Majeſty, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſt the People with vile Opinions, and wicked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits of His Sacred Perſon and Dignity. I will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thoſe Men, who maintaine the People in their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty, not to be what indeed they are, <hi>fallaciae Magiſtri,</hi> (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> calls ſome in his time) Maſters of Falſhood; and to be what indeed they are not, <hi>Magiſtri Veritatis,</hi> Maſters of Truth; and ſo all their falſe reports, true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. And notwithſtanding this ſuppoſition, I ſhall
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:30851:16"/>
make good <hi>Solomons non eſt qui reſiſtat ei,</hi> make it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent unto you, That it is not lawfull for the Subject to riſe up in Arms againſt him. You may remember I toucht upon this point formerly, I ſhall now (I hope) to your better ſatiſfaction more fully handle, what I then but lightly toucht.</p>
            <p>Our Ground-work muſt be this infallible Axiome, That <hi>It is not lawfull to take up Arms, but in the defence of a juſt Cauſe, and in Obedience to a Lawfull Command.</hi> 1. Then I will make it apparant, that there is no <hi>Cauſe.</hi> 2. That there is no <hi>Authority</hi> that can juſtifie a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject taking up Arms againſt the King. But before I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, give me leave to premiſe ſomewhat, for the preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting prejudice and miſunderſtanding (a thing too too in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident in the cauſe of Kings.) When God and the King ſtand in Subordination,<note place="margin">Note.</note> there, <hi>Deo &amp; Hominibus,</hi> we muſt obey God and Man. But where they ſtand in Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, there the Apoſtles Maxime is good, <hi>Deo potius quam Hominibus, Acts</hi> 4.19. we muſt obey God rather than Man. When then I tell you, you muſt obey wicked Kings, thinke not that I would have you obey <hi>Kings</hi> in their wickedneſſe. No. I know there is a <hi>quae Caeſaris,</hi> and a <hi>quae Dei,</hi> ſo that our Oath of Allegiance to the <hi>King,</hi> muſt be no breach of our Oath in B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ptiſme to <hi>God.</hi> As <hi>Kings</hi> Reigne, <hi>per Deum,</hi> by God, ſo muſt we obey them <hi>propter Deum,</hi> for God, not <hi>contra Deum,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God. Not, becauſe <hi>Kings</hi> are <hi>Kings,</hi> therefore, <hi>quod libet licet,</hi> their Will muſt be a Law. What were this, but to Deifie <hi>Kings;</hi> and in ſtead of <hi>Gods,</hi> by Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, to make them <hi>Gods</hi> indeed, inſtead of <hi>Dii dicti, Dii facti,</hi> and ſo wipe the firſt Commandement out of the Decalogye. We muſt know then, we are to learne a Leſſon of Obedience, even when we diſobey, Obedience
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:30851:16"/>
to the puniſhment inflicted, when we diſobey the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand enjoyn'd; yeelding though not <hi>Active Obedience</hi> to do, yet <hi>Paſsive,</hi> to ſuffer what the evill Prince lay's upon us; ſo that, as we may not obey Princes in doing the evill they Command, ſo nor may we riſe up againſt them, when they Command that which is evill. And this is the Summe of Gods Truth, and the Saints Practiſe, in this caſe of Subjection to wicked Kings. This to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move Prejudice and Miſunderſtanding, now <hi>ad Rem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. No <hi>Cauſe</hi> can juſtifie the Subjects taking up Arms againſt their <hi>King.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> No cauſe can juſtifie arms againſt the King.</note> We muſt know Satan deceives not more, than when an Angell of Light; and Rebellion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes not more, than when it's pretence is Religion and Juſtice. See that one Example of <hi>Abſolon,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. <hi>He ſteales away the Hearts of the People; and how that?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>Firſt he poſſeſſeth them with an evill opinion of the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>that he neglects the execution of Juſtice;</hi> and then inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates into them,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>That if he were made Judge in the Land</hi> (not yet ſeeming to ayme at the Crown, he onely deſires to be made a Judge in the Land) <hi>them the times ſhould be better: If any Man had any ſuite or cauſe, if he came unto him, he would doe him Juſtice.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. <hi>5.</hi> &amp;c.</note> And then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended to a winning Affability with the People, he raiſeth a moſt unnaturall Rebellion; which he colours over, not onely with the faire Pretence of executing Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, but alſo of preſerving Religion, and therefore, <hi>he offers Sacrifice before the People.</hi> And the better to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance his Rebellion, he makes uſe of <hi>Achitophell</hi> the great Councellor, and others of the Nobles of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> And if we look upon <hi>King David,</hi> he (good Man) is put to as great ſtraits as <hi>King Charles.</hi> He is driven from the great City <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> he is forc't to fly a farre off, and glad that he can be furniſht with proviſion at <hi>Maha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naim,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:30851:17"/>
at the bounty of his better Subjects. And being at this diſtance, he Aſſembles what Forces he can rayſe, and ſends them out to ſuppreſſe the Rebellion of <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon;</hi> who as he brought upon the Kingdome, the miſery of a Civill War, ſo upon himſelfe the confuſion of an unnaturall Sonne, and a Rebellious Subject. Here let me ſay to <hi>King Charles,</hi> what <hi>Cuſhi</hi> ſaid to <hi>King David,</hi> (ſince their caſe is not much unlike) when he brought the News of the Victory, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.32. <hi>Let the Enemies of my Lord the King, and all that riſe up to doe thee hurt, be as that young Man is.</hi> But that a pretended <hi>Cauſe</hi> how ſpecious ſoever, ſhould juſtifie Arms againſt the King, no Man will beleive. Therefore I muſt goe a great way farther, and draw the Cord much longer, and make it appeare; that no <hi>Cauſe,</hi> how juſt ſoever truely and indeed, can juſtifie the Subjects taking up Arms againſt their Soveraigne. What cauſe more Religious than that of Religion? What cauſe more Juſt than that of Juſtice it ſelfe? Yet neither for the Profeſſion of Religion, nor for the execution of Juſtice, may Subjects take up Arms againſt their King. This is evident. <hi>Aſhur is the Rod of Gods anger, yet muſt Iſrael be ſubject; Nebuchadnezzar his ſcourge, yet muſt</hi> Judah <hi>ſubmit,</hi> and be ſo farre from raiſing Arms againſt him, <hi>that they muſt pray for his Peace,</hi> Jer. 29.7. In that 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Prayers are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be made for</hi> Governours, who were they? not Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, but Heathens. In that 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Honour the King.</hi> Who was that? <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the good? No, but <hi>Nero</hi> the Cruell. And ſure, where God Commands Prayers to be made for <hi>Kings,</hi> Horour and Obedience to be given to <hi>Kings,</hi> he takes away taking up Arms againſt <hi>Kings;</hi> though ſuch as <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> ſuch as <hi>Nero,</hi> Idolatrous and Cruell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:30851:17"/>
               <hi>Bleſſed are they</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>who ſuffer perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for Righteouſneſſe ſake, for their's is the Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> Math. 5.10. not Bleſſed are they who rayſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion for Righteouſneſſe ſake, that theirs may be the Kingdomes of the Earth. And againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 44.</note> 
               <hi>Love your Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, bleſſe them that curſe you, and pray for them which deſpightfully uſe you, and perſecute you;</hi> and the reaſon is, <hi>ut Filii ſitis, That ye may be the Children;</hi> the Children of whom? <hi>Filii hujus ſeculi,</hi> Children of this World? no; Fleſh and Blood cannot endure this; they are for another Way, a Way of Oppoſition, a Way of Rebellion; but <hi>Filii Patris veſtri qui eſt in Caelis, the Children of your Father which is in Heaven.</hi> If then to love our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to Bleſſe them that Curſe us, to doe good to them that here us, and to Pray for them who deſpightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſe us and perſecute us, be <hi>Godly, Spirituall, and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly;</hi> then to have bitter Envyings and Strifes in the Heart, to rayſe Civill Diſſention and Diviſion in the State, is <hi>Earthly, Senſuall and Divelliſh,</hi> as S. <hi>James</hi> ſpeaks <hi>ch.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 15. S. <hi>Peter</hi> in 1 <hi>Ep. c.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 18. He admoniſheth Servants to be ſubject to their Maſters, <hi>with all Feare, not only to the Good and Gentle, Alla kai tois skoliois, but alſo to the Froward,</hi> ſo our Engliſh, <hi>pravis</hi> the wicked; ſo <hi>Beza: duris,</hi> hard or cruell; ſo <hi>Tremelius.</hi> And if Servants muſt obey wicked and cruell Maſters, then muſt Subjects obey Wicked and Cruell Kings; for the ſame relation that the Servant hath to his Maſter, the ſame hath the Subject to his <hi>King.</hi> And <hi>Beza's</hi> note here concerning the Servant, may, not unfitly, be applyed to the Subject; That, <hi>though his condition ſeem in this caſe very grievous, yet his ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction ſhall be ſo much the more accoptable to God, ſi volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ipſius plus valeat quam Dominorum injuriae; If the good pleaſure of his will more prevaile with them, than the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:30851:18"/>
injury's of their Lords.</hi> Again in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.19. <hi>Dearely beloved</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) avenge not your ſelves:</hi> If we may not avenge our ſelves upon our Equalls, much leſſe upon our Superiours, and leaſt of all (that is, not at all) on him who is Supreame,<note place="margin">Comment in locum.</note> 
               <hi>Ergo affligemur inulti,</hi> ſhall we then be tyrannized over without Revenge? <hi>Muſculus</hi> makes the Objection, and gives the anſwer; <hi>adjecta eſt,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>hujus gratia, aſſertio illa, ego rependam,</hi> For this cauſe, is that Aſſertion added, <hi>I will repay,</hi> ſaith the Lord; and <hi>a fearefull thing it is to fall into the hands of the living God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10 11.</note> and <hi>ideo horribilius Regibus,</hi> therefore the more fearefull for <hi>Kings,</hi> becauſe they have him alone to be their Judge, and, <hi>quid credimus judicem illum, ſi non &amp; ultorem?</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſpeaks, Wherefore doe we beleive him a Judge, if not a Revenger? As for <hi>Kings</hi> then, God will puniſh them <hi>Autocheir,</hi> with his own hand; which <hi>David</hi> knew well, when he anſwered <hi>Abiſhai</hi> (moving, yea, inciting him to ſlay <hi>Saul,</hi> or ſuffer <hi>Saul</hi> to be ſlaine) with a <hi>Deus percuſſerit, God ſhall ſmite him;</hi> but as for himſelfe, he would not <hi>ſtretch out his hand againſt him,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.6.10.11. I could heape up Texts of Scripture to confirme this Truth, but this one ſentence of my Text may ſuffice; where we have it <hi>propriis terminis</hi> (a thing now a dayes ſo much ſtood upon) <hi>A King againſt whom there is no riſing up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we deſire Examples for further confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let us retire backe to former. Ages, and we are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks upon another occaſion) <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed about with a cloud of Witneſſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Nephos marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rwn,</hi> a cloud of Martyrs, ſealing and maintaining Gods Truth, with their owne Blood, not with the Blood of others. Was not <hi>Saul</hi> a bloody Perſecutor, ſlaying <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech,</hi> with fourſcore and foure Prieſts in one Day, upon
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:30851:18"/>
the falſe accuſation of <hi>Doeg?</hi> was he not a Demoniacke, poſſeſſed with an evill Spirit? a cruell Tyrant, ſeeking not onely the death of <hi>David,</hi> but alſo of <hi>Jonathan</hi> his owne Sonne? Yet when God had delivered him into <hi>Davids</hi> hands, and <hi>Abiſhai</hi> (looking upon him onely with a Souldiers Eye, as his Enemy) had been earneſt to kill him; yet ſaith <hi>David, deſtroy him not, for who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords Anoynted, and be guiltleſſe?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9. The <hi>Lords Anoynted!</hi> What <hi>Saul</hi> a Perſecutor, a Doemoniacke, a Tyrant, and yet <hi>Chriſtus Domini,</hi> the <hi>Lords Anoynted?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> Here (beloved) let me give you a remarkeable Obſervation; This Anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting here, doth not betoken any Spirituall Grace, as elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where it doth in ſeverall places of the Scriptures; a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake (let me tell you) which hath begotten many irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent opinions concerning <hi>Kings.</hi> Royall Unction gives a Juſt Title to the Crowne, not divine Grace to ſway the Scepter; it gives Right to rule, not to Rule rightly. Though true it is, it were much to be wiſh't, that Grace in their Hearts, were as fragrant, as the oyle upon their Heads; and that, as they excell in Glory and Dignity, ſo in Godlineſſe and vertue. But we ſee wicked <hi>Saul</hi> then, as well as holy <hi>David,</hi> is <hi>Chriſtus Domini,</hi> the Lords Anoynted; he had (as all wicked Kings have) <hi>ſanctitatem <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nctionis,</hi> though not <hi>ſanctitatem vitae,</hi> an holy Calling though not an holy Life. Yea, <hi>the Lord ruleth in the Kingdom of Men, and giveth it to whomſoever he will,</hi> ſo the Prophet <hi>Daniel, c.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 32. ſo that he may be <hi>Chriſtus</hi> who is not <hi>Chriſtianus</hi> as was <hi>Darius</hi> the Heathen, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 45.1. If then <hi>Kings</hi> are made <hi>Chriſti Domini,</hi> the Lords Anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, neither for Religion nor Vertue; then certainly, they may not be unmade for either Hereſie or Vice, according to that Divinity axiome, <hi>dominium temporale non funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:30851:19"/>
in gratia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Saliſ. deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minat. Comment in locum.</note> temporall Dominion (or power of Rule) is not founded upon Grace. To all this accords that of <hi>Junius,</hi> and <hi>Tremelius, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncto Jehovae</hi> (ſay they) the Anoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of the Lord, that is, <hi>a Deo ad Regnum aſſumpto,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by God to the Kingdome; and what? to have his Crown preſently caſt down to the ground, and himſelfe upon miſdemeanour depoſed from his Throne by the States, by the multitude, by the Collective body of the Kingdom, as ſome would have it? no, <hi>a Deo ad Regnum aſſumpto, ac proinde ſancto, &amp; munito ab omni injuria,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by God to the Kingdom, and therefore ſacred and fortified from all Injury.<note place="margin">Note.</note> In that great defection under <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> did there not live many holy Prophets? in that hot Perſecution under <hi>Nero,</hi> did there not live many holy Apoſtles? under that grand Apoſtacy of <hi>Julian,</hi> did there not live many holy Fathers? yet (I will ſpeak it <hi>ex animo</hi>) let it appear that there was ever any one Prophet, any one Apoſtle, any one Father, that ſtirred up ſedition, or moved the People to take up Arm's (though in their defence) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Soveraign; and I will ſubmit to their Cenſure who now oppoſe their King, &amp; I think I could not expect more ſevere Iudges. Run over the Acts of the Apoſtles and you ſhall find them in the Priſon, not in the Campe; drawne before <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> not drawing <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; ſtoned but not ſtoning; ſtruck with the Sword, but not ſtriking with the Sword. And in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.4. <hi>We glory in you</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>in the churches of God;</hi> for what? for their Valour and Courage in defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Goſpell by force of Arms? no, but for their <hi>Patience and Faith, in all their Perſecutions and Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations for the Goſpell.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 42.</note> Aske Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and Learned Father) how Paganiſme and Hereſie was vanquiſht, and how the Truth of the Goſpell was main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained? and he will tell you, <hi>non a repugnantibus, ſed a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:30851:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
morientibus Chriſtianis,</hi> nor by Chriſtians reſiſting, but by Chriſtians dying. What thinke you now? who are the beſt Chriſtians, they who take up the Croſſe and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, or they who take up Arms and reſiſt their Soveraigne?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> But ſome may ſay; The former Chriſtians did not take up Arms, and a good reaſon why, they had no Arms to take up; or if they had, they were ſo far Inferiour in number and Power, that they durſt not take them up. But, what think you of that which <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us of in his Greek Fragments? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſ."/> That when <hi>Plinius Secundus</hi> obſerved the numerous Company of Chriſtians which ſuffered Martyrdome for the Faith of Chriſt; <hi>tarach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theis tw plethei, multitudine interremptorum permotus</hi> (as <hi>Ruffinus</hi> Tranſlates it <hi>Paraphraſticws</hi>) aſtoniſhed at the Multitude of them that were ſlaine, he related to the Emperour, <hi>quod innumera hominum millia quotidie ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truncarentur,</hi> that innumerable thouſands of Men were ſlaine dayly (as the ſame <hi>Ruffinus</hi> tells us) what ſo many thouſands ſlaine, <hi>&amp; quotidie</hi> too, ſlaine every day? how eaſie had it been (having the Lord of Hoſts on their ſide) to have gathered themſelves together in every Province, and to have ſtood, not onely for the Truth, but alſo for their Lives; and <hi>to have deſtroyed, to have ſlaine, and to have cauſed to periſh all the Power of the People, and of the Provinces that ſhould have aſſaulted them,</hi> as did the Jews, (yet not without Commiſſion from <hi>Ahaſuerus) Eſth.</hi> 8.11. But we ſee the contrary affirm'd to their Faces with a Challenge, in <hi>Nazianzens</hi> Oration. 2. <hi>contra</hi> Julian; <hi>In quos veſtrum</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>populum exaeſtuantem contra vos infurgere ſolicitavimw? quibus vitae periculum attulimus?</hi> Againſt whom of you have we moved the Tumultuous People to riſe up? Which of you have we put in danger
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:30851:20"/>
of his Life? They <hi>had not ſo learned Chriſt.</hi> They knew well, <hi>The Kingdom of Heaven ſuffereth violence, and the violent take it by force;</hi> but what Violence? of oppoſing? no, but of ſuffering. What Force? of arm's? no, but of a godly life. They knew well, if God had intended the founding his Church, the propagating his Truth, by an Arme of Fleſh, by the Power of the Temporall Sword, he who is <hi>kardiognwſtes,</hi> the ſearcher of the Heart, is alſo <hi>kardiotreptes,</hi> the mover of the Heart; and ſo would have moved the Hearts of <hi>Kings,</hi> rather then the hearts of the People; he would have called the Wiſe, the Mighty, and the Noble, rather than the fooliſh, the baſe, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed. But <hi>that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence,</hi> and that <hi>Gods</hi> Strength might appeare in Mans Weakeneſſe, he <hi>choſe the fooliſh things of the world to confound the Wiſe, the Weake things to confound the things which are Mighty, and baſe things of the World and things which are deſpiſed, did God chuſe; yea, things which are not to bring to naught things that are,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.26.27. &amp;c. That of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> to <hi>Demetrianus</hi> is full to our purpoſe; none of us (ſaith he) when he is apprehended reſiſteth, <hi>quamvis ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius &amp; copioſus noſter ſit numerus,</hi> though our number be far the greater. Above all, Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtory relates, that <hi>Julians</hi> Army (notwithſtanding his great cruelty and perſecution) did conſiſt moſt of Chriſtians, who (we reade) fought for him againſt his Enemies, but never for themſelves againſt him; and that his Army did conſiſt moſt of Chriſtians, appears by that full Acclamation of theirs to <hi>Jovinian</hi> afrer <hi>Julians</hi> death, <hi>Chriſtiani ſumus,</hi> we are Chriſtians. So that we may well ſay with <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian,</hi> concerning the Sect of Chriſtians in their Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions, <hi>occidi licet, occidere non licet;</hi> not <hi>occidi poteſt, occidere non poteſt;</hi> not, that it is in their Power to be ſlain,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:30851:20"/>
not in their <hi>Power</hi> to ſlay; but, it is <hi>Lawfull</hi> for them to be ſlaine, not <hi>Lawfull</hi> for them to ſlay. <hi>Solomon</hi> here confirm's it with a <hi>non eſt qui reſiſtat,</hi> there is not any that may reſiſt.</p>
            <p>Yet are not the Adverſary's herewith ſatisfied,<note place="margin">The Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</note> but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to us the Men of Jeruſalem who roſe up againſt King <hi>Amaziah,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 14.19. Yet ſee how the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſetts a brand upon them, and tells us, that <hi>conſpirave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant conſpirationem,</hi> they made a great Conſpiracy; an act as little commendable, as it is imitable. They tell us of the ten Tribes falling away to <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> though the Scripture tells us, that it was of the Lord, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 12.24. <hi>Jeroboam</hi> being anoynted to the Crown by <hi>Ahijah</hi> the Shilonite. They tell us of <hi>Jehu</hi> ſmiting the Houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and riſing up in arms againſt <hi>Joram</hi> his King, though the Scripture tells us, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 9.6. Thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>I have anoynted thee King over Iſrael;</hi> and ſo <hi>Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi> well, It was an act extraordinary,<note place="margin">Loc. com. cla. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; non in Exemplum trahendum,</hi> and not to be drawn into example. They tell us alſo of the People delivering <hi>Jonathan</hi> from <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.45. Though it appears not in Scripture, that they did it by forceable arms of reſiſtance, but rather (as <hi>Junius</hi> and <hi>Tremelius</hi>) by forceable Argument of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, <hi>ut poſthabita juramenti ratione,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Comment in locum.</note> 
               <hi>juris haberetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem,</hi> That laying aſide the account he had of his Oath, he would have reſpect to Equity and Juſtice. Thus then, notwithſtanding the Oppoſition of the Adverſaries, I have made it cleare to you, that no <hi>Cauſe</hi> can juſtifie the Subjects taking up arms againſt the King.</p>
            <p n="2">2 No <hi>Authority.</hi> Who ſhall command againſt him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> No autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</note> from whom iſſueth the Power of commanding? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> Yea, but he is entruſted with that Power by the Commonwealth, for the ſafety and well fare thereof, which if he abuſeth,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:30851:21"/>
he may be deprived of it, by the Commonwealth. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Anſ."/> Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe this true (as you know affirm'd it hath been for a Truth) ſuppoſe our King had his Power committed to him by the State (which yet is moſt falſe, as ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently appeare) and ſuppoſe it in the Power of the State, to require it of him again (Though let me tell you, this ſevering the Head from the Body, the King from the State, hath been as ominous as erroneus. But as I leade you into this Maze,<note place="margin">Note.</note> ſo will I conduct you out again.) Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this Suppoſition then, conſider well our many He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro's, brave Worthies, Starres <hi>primae magnitudinis,</hi> ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning no leſſe in Valour than in Vertue; conſider the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of their Wiſedome, the Authority of their Perſons, the Uprightneſſe of their Lives, Men fit for Councell in Peace, and Conduct in Warre. Conſider thoſe great Nobles, and Grave Judges of the Land; the Learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Clergy of the Land; the Faithfull Gentry, and Loyall Commonalty; conſider the great Counties, the many Cities, with the Famous Univerſities: All which ſtand up in the defence of their Soveraigne, the Lords anoynted. Conſider theſe well, and then tell me, what is that you call the State? what is that you call the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth of the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, that not without cauſe Saint <hi>Jude</hi> tells us, <hi>v.</hi> 8. that they who deſpiſe Governement, <hi>kurioteta,</hi> not <hi>Dominum,</hi> but <hi>Dominatum,</hi> not the Governours, but the Governement;<note place="margin">Comment in locum.</note> 
               <hi>ordinem ipſum a Deo conſtitutum,</hi> ſo <hi>Beza,</hi> the Order it ſelfe conſtituted by God. They (the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle tells u ) are <hi>'Enupnazourenoi, altiſsimo veterno ſopiri,</hi> buried in a dead ſleep, ſo <hi>Beza</hi> againe; they are <hi>filthy Dreamers,</hi> ſo our Engliſh; <hi>deluſi inſomniis,</hi> deluded with Dreames, ſo <hi>Eraſmus.</hi> That of our Engliſh may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, to the great Stateſmen, the Patriots; that of <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:30851:21"/>
to the People, their Diſciples; the former they are filthy Dreamers; the latter, they are <hi>deluſi inſomniis,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived with their Dreames. For is it not evident to him that is awake, and his Eyes open; That what thoſe Men ſet down to juſtifie their Actions, doe moſt of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne them, they ſwerving from their own Principles? <hi>But to returne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Power of <hi>Kings is de ſuper,</hi> nor <hi>de ſubter,</hi> from above, not from beneath; from God,<note place="margin">From whence the power of Kings is.</note> not from the Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>jects; call them what you will, the Multitude, the States, or the Commonwealth, <hi>Ego dixi Dii eſtis,</hi> Pſal. 82.6. I have ſaid ye are Gods; <hi>Ego dixi,</hi> I have ſaid, not <hi>nos diximus,</hi> We have ſaid; he hath ſaid it, whoſe <hi>Dixit,</hi> is a <hi>Fecit,</hi> by him are Kings ordain'd, by whom all things are created; <hi>Per me Reges per quem Regna,</hi> by him are <hi>Kings,</hi> by whom are Kingdomes; the World, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of the World, hath the ſame <hi>per,</hi> both <hi>pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatis &amp; perſonae,</hi> of Power and of Perſon; If wicked Men once ſeparate <hi>Reges,</hi> from <hi>per me,</hi> Kings, from him by whom they are Kings, no wonder if they ſtrike at <hi>Regnant</hi> too, no wonder if they ſtrive to caſt their Crowns down to the ground, and lay their Honour in the duſt. <hi>Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> is full for an Heathen Emperour;<note place="margin">In Apologet.</note> 
               <hi>Imperatorem</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>neceſſe eſt ut ſuſpiciamus,</hi> it is neceſſary that we reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the Emperour; and how ſo? <hi>ut eum quem Dominus noſter elegit,</hi> as him whom our Lord hath choſen; <hi>ut me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito dixerim noſter eſt magis Caeſar, ut a noſtro Deo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutus,</hi> that I may very well ſay, <hi>Caeſar</hi> is rather our Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, as conſtituted by our God. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> Yea, the King is by God; but God he worketh by means, and therfore though he chuſe the King, yet it is <hi>mediante Populo,</hi> by the choice of the People. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="Object."/> For this ſee, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.20. there ſaith God of King <hi>David, I have exalted one choſen out
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:30851:22"/>
of the People<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">The King not choſen by the People.</note> 
               <hi>Electum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Populo,</hi> choſen out of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; not <hi>electum a Populo,</hi> choſen by the People, <hi>qui exaltavit, etiam elegit,</hi> by him he was choſen, by whom he was exalted; by him he was choſen out of the People, by whom he was exalted above the People. And as for King <hi>David,</hi> ſo for all the <hi>Kings</hi> of his Race, God hath a <hi>per me</hi> for them all; and as for them, ſo for all <hi>Kings</hi> elſe by lawfull Succeſſion, that is, <hi>certum &amp; deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minatum;</hi> As for unlawfull Uſurpation, I leave that <hi>ſub Judice,</hi> as needing no Sentence at the preſent. If then the King receives not his Power from the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, then cannot the Commonwealth, either take away the Power from the King, or exerciſe a Power and Command againſt the King. Thus then, if no <hi>Cauſe,</hi> no <hi>Authority</hi> can juſtifie armes againſt the King, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Cauſe</hi> Men pretend, whatſoever <hi>Authority</hi> they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, <hi>Solomon</hi> ſtands up ſtill for the King with his <hi>non eſt qui reſiſtat ei,</hi> there is not any that may reſiſt him. But here I muſt not paſſe neither, without a ſtand.</p>
            <p>The ſeverall places of Scripture, which yeeld either Precept or Example of <hi>Obedience</hi> to Kings (though wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked) there are thoſe who evade the Force of them, by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying them to private or Particular Men, and ſo runnes indeed the whole Current of Antimonarchians. And therefore ſay they; the Magiſtrates under the King though <hi>ſinguli ſeparatim</hi> each one ſeverall be his inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, yet <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi conjunctim,</hi> all conjoyn'd are his Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour. By the way obſerve, <hi>ut dicta factis deficientibus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubeſcant,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian (de Patientia)</hi> ſpeakes, That their Writings may ſhame their Actions. Their owne Tenet is, That if the Magiſtrates be above the King, they muſt be <hi>univerſi conjunctim,</hi> all conjoyn'd; not divided, and ſo,<note place="margin">Note.</note> as that the leſſe part prevaile over the greater. Which perchance may be true, as concerning a Duke of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:30851:22"/>
Venice (as you have formerly had the Example) or a Prince of Orange; but moſt certainly not as concerning a King of England. Therefore (Beloved) beware of thoſe kind of Stateſmen, who following their Maſters, would firſt bring us to a low King, and after that (I feare) a Low-Country too. <hi>Buchanan</hi> a great Patron of this Faction tells us, <hi>quaſi ex Tripode,</hi> with as much confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as if it were an Oracle <hi>(in Dialog. de jure Reg.) jus idem habere in Reges multitudinem, quod illi in ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los e multitudine habent:</hi> It is too poyſonous to be Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed. Thus ſometimes the States, ſometimes the Multitude in theſe Mens opinions, muſt <hi>ſupereminere,</hi> be Supreame; and not the King in Saint <hi>Peters.</hi> But what? ſhall we beleive <hi>Buchanan</hi> and the Preſbytery, or Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and others of the Apoſtles? <hi>cui potius ſigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram vocis ſuae declaraſſet, quam cui figuram gloriae ſuae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velavit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) to whom ſhould Chriſt have reveal'd his will, rather than to whom he reveal'd his Glory; namely, Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt. I will not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe your patience, nor miſuſemy paines to enlarge a Confutation; <hi>vel recitaſſe, eſt confutaſſe,</hi> to have recited them, is to have confuted them. Onely obſerve, that the Practiſes of thoſe in our times who oppoſe the King, are falne beſides the Foundation layd them by their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, for if they look their Leſſon over again, they ſhall find; that not a part or parcell of the Magiſtrates, but <hi>univerſi conjunctim,</hi> all conjoyn'd; not <hi>aliqui e multitudine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> 
               <hi>ſed multitudinem,</hi> not ſome Companies of the Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, but the whole Multitude; not <hi>unus aut alter de judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus, aut Principibus Regni,</hi> one or two (that is, ſome few) of the Judges or Nobles of the Kingdom; but they are <hi>univerſi Regni ordines,</hi> the whole States of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, who may either <hi>moderari coercere,</hi> or <hi>punire Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipem.</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:30851:23"/>
Thus as <hi>Job</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 13. God taketh the Wiſe, <hi>'En panourgia 'autwn,</hi> ſaith the Septuagint, in their ſubtle wilineſſe, and the councell of the froward is carryed headlong, <hi>conſilium reluctantium,</hi> ſo <hi>Junius;</hi> the councell of the Rebellious, not deviſed with more folly, than proſecuted with fury, to their own deſtruction.</p>
            <p>I will conclude this point then, with that place in the Church Homilyes (ſo full againſt wilfull Rebellion, That certainly Satan intending to raiſe Rebellion in the People, firſt thought it neceſſary to ſuppreſſe the Homilies from the People.) The Words are theſe, <hi>Turne over and reade the Hiſtories of all Nations, look over the Cronicles of our own Country, call to memory ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Rebellions of old time, and ſome yet freſh in Memory; and we ſhall finde, That, were the Multitudes of the Rebells never ſo huge and great, the Captains never ſo Noble, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke and Witty, the pretences feigned never ſo good and holy; yet the ſpeedy overthrow of all Rebells, of what Number, State, or Condition ſoever they were, or what colour or cauſe ſoever they pretended, is, and ever hath been ſuch, that God thereby doth ſhew, that he alloweth neither the dignity of any Perſon, nor the Multitude of any People, nor the weight of any cauſe, as ſufficient for the which the Subjects may move Rebellion againſt their Princes,</hi> Thus far the Homily's of the Church. And if thus no <hi>Cauſe,</hi> no <hi>Authority</hi> againſt a wicked King,<note place="margin">Note.</note> much leſſe can any <hi>Cauſe,</hi> any <hi>Authority</hi> juſtifie Arms againſt a gracious King. If <hi>Jeremy</hi> will have Subjection to Idol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trous <hi>Nebuchadnezzar;</hi> if Chriſt to Heathen <hi>Caeſar;</hi> if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to Perſecuting <hi>Nero;</hi> who ſhall deny it to pious King <hi>Charles?</hi> If for any King, then ſure for our King; <hi>Solomon's non eſt qui reſiſtat ei,</hi> ſtands good, <hi>There is not any that may reſiſt him.</hi> Thus of the Words as denying <hi>rem factam,</hi> the thing done, and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:30851:23"/>
               <hi>jus facti,</hi> the lawfulneſſe of doing the thing. I will briefely runne over the reſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Quomodo</hi> the <hi>Manner,</hi> how <hi>there is no riſing up,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1. Quomodo</hi> the manner how there is no riſing up. <hi>1. Non Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de,</hi> not in the Heart.</note> and firſt, <hi>non corde,</hi> no riſing up in the Heart, <hi>malum cogitando,</hi> in thinking evill. Rebellion is the rankeſt poyſon, the leaſt drop whereof is deadly; not onely the large <hi>quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> but the leaſt <hi>Scruple</hi> is forbidden, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 10.20. <hi>Curſe not the King in thy thought;</hi> the very hatching of a Cockatribe Egge is poyſon, as well as the Viper; the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of Treaſon is a Sinne of an high nature, as well as the Action, and if proved, ſhall be equally puniſhed. <hi>Eſth.</hi> 2.22. it is ſaid of <hi>Bigthan</hi> and <hi>Tereſh,</hi> that <hi>voluerunt inſurgere,</hi> not that they did <hi>riſe up,</hi> but that they would <hi>have riſen up</hi> againſt <hi>Ahaſuerus;</hi> though but a <hi>voluerunt</hi> an intention onely without action, yet treaſon, for which they are adjudged to death. <hi>Touch not mine Anoynted</hi> (ſaith the Lord, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 105.15. <hi>Noljte tangere,</hi> not the hand onely to act, but the Heart alſo to will, is forbidden. Not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly then for this Cauſe (though for others too more fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) Kings are called Gods, becauſe of the divine Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge communicated to them from God; that as againſt God, ſo againſt the King, <hi>ſufficit cor,</hi> the Heart is enough; therefore <hi>nemo inſurgit,</hi> no riſing up <hi>corde;</hi> in the Heart, <hi>malum cogitando,</hi> in thinking evill.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Non Lingua,</hi> no <hi>riſing up</hi> with the <hi>Tongue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Non Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua,</hi> not in the Tongue.</note> 
               <hi>maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendo,</hi> in ſpeaking evill. In that 21. <hi>v.</hi> of Saint <hi>Iudes</hi> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, it was <hi>contradictio,</hi> the gainſaying of <hi>Core,</hi> in which he and his Company periſhed. If the defacing of the <hi>Kings</hi> Picture be Treaſon, what think you is the diſgracing the <hi>Kings</hi> Perſon? <hi>veni &amp; maledic,</hi> come and curſe, where God hath bleſſed is <hi>Balaam's</hi> Office; to rayle and revile whom God hath humbled (eſpecially if a King) is <hi>Shimei's</hi> practiſe, neither ſit for imitation, neither fit for a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:30851:24"/>
againſt his Soveraigne. The King is the Father of his Country; and as for the Naturall Father, ſo for the Politicall, <hi>maledictus qui vilipendit,</hi> curſed is he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth him; yea, and <hi>qui maledicit,</hi> who ſpeaketh evill of him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 27.16. curſed, and that with a mount <hi>Ebal's</hi> curſe, a curſe to which many have formerly ſaid <hi>Amen,</hi> who now are in Arms againſt their <hi>Politicall</hi> Father the King. Thus <hi>nemo inſurgit,</hi> no riſing up, <hi>Lingua,</hi> with the Tongue, <hi>maledicendo,</hi> in ſpeaking evill.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3. Non ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu,</hi> not with the hand.</note>3. <hi>Non Manu, no riſing up</hi> with the <hi>Hand, malefaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endo,</hi> in doing evill, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26.9. <hi>Who can ſtretch forth his Hand againſt the Lords Anoynted and be guiltleſſe? Quis,</hi> Who can? that is, <hi>nullus,</hi> no Man can. This the <hi>triumphant Negative</hi> (as one calls it) a <hi>Negative</hi> with a Challenge. We have ſome with <hi>Jacobs</hi> Voyce, though <hi>Eſav's</hi> hands, who tell us, they take up armes in the <hi>Kings</hi> Defence, (though this Defence be his greateſt danger) but I que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, whether, if they had <hi>Davids</hi> opportunity, they would have <hi>Davids</hi> reſolution, of not ſtretching out their hand againſt him. Obſerve in <hi>David</hi> here, not onely a <hi>ne perdas</hi> (in the former part of the verſe) a giving of the blow; but a <hi>ne Manum mittas</hi> in the latter) a ſtirring of the Hand, is forbidden. Therefore as <hi>nemo inſurgit,</hi> no ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up, <hi>corde,</hi> in the Heart, <hi>malum cogitando,</hi> in thinking evill, <hi>Lingua,</hi> with the Tongue, <hi>male dicendo,</hi> in ſpeaking evill; ſo eſpecially, <hi>nemo inſurgit,</hi> no riſing up, <hi>Manu,</hi> with the Hand, <hi>malefaciendo,</hi> in doing evill.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. quare,</hi> the Reaſon why.</note>2. <hi>Quare,</hi> the Reaſon, why there is no riſing up. 1. Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from <hi>malum culpae,</hi> the evill of Sinne. 2. <hi>Malum paena,</hi> the evill of Puniſhment, it is but borrowed of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>He that reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God,</hi> ther's the <hi>malum culpae,</hi> the evill of Sin, and <hi>they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves damnation,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:30851:24"/>
ther's the <hi>malum paenae,</hi> the evill of Puniſhment. The former Argument is for the Godly, who are moved <hi>cum timore Dei,</hi> with the feare of God. The latter is for the ungodly, <hi>quos ut magis moveat</hi> (ſaith <hi>Muſculus</hi>) whom that he might the more ſtrongly move, he comes upon them, <hi>metu Judicii,</hi> with the feare of Judgement.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then <hi>malum culpae,</hi> the evill of Sinne. If a Rebell were askt his Name, how well might he anſwer with the Man poſſeſſed with Devills, that his name is <hi>Legion,</hi> for they are many. Rebellion being a Neſt of Devills, a Sinke of all Sinnes, a Maſſe of all Impieties; what Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>faneſſe, what Murders, what Robberies, what Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, what Malice, what Hatred, what Miſchiefe is it that you can name, which is not heapt up in this Chaos of Confuſion, this one manyfold Sinne, Rebellion? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in the State, is like an Impoſtume in the Body, which breaking inwardly, diſtempers and corrupts the whole, and makes it's recovery deſperate. So that to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe Diſorders, by diſſorderly Commotions, to compoſe Diſtractions by Rebellion, is all one, as if a Man ſhould quench fire with pitch, or cure old ſores with new plagues <hi>Better</hi> therefore (as our Church ſpeaks in her Homily's againſt wilfull Rebellion) <hi>undergo the worſt of Governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, then the worſt of miſeries, Rebellion the Deſtruction of all Governement, a right Apollyon, bringing ruine upon all States.</hi> ſo that as the Lacedemonians, to cauſe their Chidren to loath drunkennes, cauſed them to behold their Servants when they were drunke; ſo that you may abominate Rebellion, it is enough if you look upon thoſe mens actions who are <hi>Rebells,</hi> for then will this <hi>Reaſon</hi> appeare good, that <hi>there is no riſing vp againſt the King,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2. Malum paenae,</hi> the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</note>
               <hi>propter malum culpae, for the evill of Sinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Malum paenae,</hi> the evill of puniſhment, why? what
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:30851:25"/>
is the puniſhment of a <hi>Rebell?</hi> Death. What death? an ignominious death, an untimely death, a painfull death, <hi>vt ſentiat ſe mori</hi> (as he in <hi>Seneca</hi>) whether it be that of <hi>Bigtham</hi> and <hi>Tereſh Eſth.</hi> 2.23. or that of <hi>Sheba</hi> 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.22, or that of <hi>Baana</hi> and <hi>Rechab,</hi> 2. Sam. 4.12. and to this adde that of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109. his Lands and Eſtate are confiſcate, his Poſterity diſgrac't and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger'd, his Name quite blotted out, or if remembred, he is <hi>damnatae memoriae,</hi> a Man whoſe Memory doth ſtinke, and is corrupted. This Puniſhment is Temporall, far ſhort of that which is Eternall, when he ſhall goe to his owne place, where with the Arch-Rebell Satan, he ſhall ſuffer the hotteſt flames in Hell, who hath rayſed ſo great a fire in the State. Thus then <hi>nemo inſurgit,</hi> no riſing up, <hi>propter malum Paenae,</hi> for the evill of Puniſhment. I will end all in a few Words of Application.</p>
            <p>Becauſe (Beloved) I have not gravity enough to be the Speaker, take it as ſpoken from the <hi>Ancient of dayes,</hi> even God himſelfe, <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21. <hi>Fili mi, time Deum &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, My ſon, fear thou God and the King, and meddle not with them who are given to change; for their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knowes the ruine of them both?</hi> Here God ſeems to ſtand as a Father, as a Judge; as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his advice is loving, <hi>My Son fear thou God and the King, and meddle not with them who are given to change;</hi> as a Judge, his ſentence is ſevere, <hi>Their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knows the ruine of them both?</hi> As we behave our ſelves, we ſhall finde the benefit of his Councell, or the penalty of his Sentence, It's added, <note n="*" place="margin">Cajet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vult hanc ſententi am eſſeancipi tem &amp; poſſe quidem ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedentes ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentias clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentes eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ordiri.</note> 
               <hi>Theſe things belong to the Wiſe,</hi> to them who either are, or would be accounted Wiſe; ſuch as are the Fathers of the State, no ſhame for them to be <hi>Solomons</hi> Sons, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this Fatherly Councell, which if they doe not,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:30851:25"/>
though they will be <hi>Iudges</hi> themſelues, yet God a Iudge above them, hath paſt their <hi>Sentence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give me leave to reveiw the Words by way of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe; ſince they ſo much reflect upon the Text, by way of Comment; and may (not unfitly) conclude my S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon by way of Application; <hi>My Son, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ear thou God and the King;</hi> Here a fit place for <hi>Davids quam bonum &amp; ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum,</hi> Pſal. 133.1. how good and joyfull a thing it is to ſee? to ſee what? why, to ſee God and the King in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction; and we know our Saviours axiome, <hi>quos Deus conjunxit, nemo ſeparet,</hi> whom God hath joyned let no Man put aſunder. He that ſeparates God from the <hi>King,</hi> ſeparates himſelfe from God. But why feare God and the King? becauſe no Man doth rightly feare the <hi>King,</hi> unleſſe he alſo feare God; neither doth any Man truely fear God, unleſſe he alſo fear the <hi>King.</hi> Feare the <hi>King</hi> in a Loyall ſubjection, not put him into a feare by unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Rebellion. <hi>Feare God and the King, and meddle not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cum muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus. So Cajet vi, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lazar expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. en Prov. Solomon.</note> meddle not with whom? <hi>cum detractoribus,</hi> with them, who are given to Detraction, ſo the Vulgar, <hi>cum variis,</hi> with them that are given to change, ſo <hi>Junius</hi> and our Engliſh; <hi>cum ſeditioſis,</hi> with them who are given to ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo others. The Word and the Sence will beare all three.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then, <hi>ne commiſcearis cum detractoribus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ne cum detractori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> meddle not with them who are given to Detraction. Detraction is ever the forerunner, and the fomenter of Sedition. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aaron <hi>take too much upon them,</hi> ſo <hi>Corah</hi> and his Company, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16, 3. Or, <hi>there is no Man ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the King to do Juſtice,</hi> ſo <hi>Alſolon,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.3. Or <hi>too heavy a yoke is layd by the King, upon the necks of the People,</hi> ſo they who fell away to <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 12.4. Therefore, <hi>ne cum detractoribus,</hi> meddle not with them who are given to <hi>detraction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:30851:26"/>
               <note place="margin">2. Ne cum variis.</note>2. <hi>Ne cum variis,</hi> meddle not with them who are given to <hi>Change.</hi> Upon <hi>Detraction,</hi> is buz'd into the People a deſire of <hi>Change. Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> take too much upon them, and therefore <hi>their Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity muſt be leſſened;</hi> the King takes no care of Juſtice, and therefore <hi>the Power of Iuſtice muſt be by others communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated;</hi> the Yoke is too heavy upon the Peoples neck's, and therefore, <hi>Their liberty muſt be enlarged.</hi> Therefore <hi>ne cum variis,</hi> meddle not with them who are given to <hi>Change.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. Ne cum ſeditioſis.</note>3. <hi>Ne cum Seditioſis,</hi> meddle not with them who are given to <hi>Sedition.</hi> Upon <hi>Detraction,</hi> men are put upon a deſire of <hi>Change,</hi> and upon that growes <hi>Sedition. Corah</hi> and his Company then <hi>aſſemble; Abſolon</hi> with his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices then <hi>make warre;</hi> the People with their Patriot, then <hi>Deſert</hi> their <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>enter the field againſt the Lords Anoynted.</hi> Thus <hi>Shimei's</hi> rayling, ends in <hi>Sheba's</hi> riſing; <hi>Detraction</hi> ends in <hi>Sedition. Defiling</hi> of <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> begetts <hi>Deſpiſing; Deſpiſing</hi> begetts <hi>Oppoſing; Oppoſing</hi> begetts <hi>Removing,</hi> and <hi>Removing</hi> begetts <hi>Ruine.</hi> Therefore in that the Wiſman adviſeth, with a <hi>Ne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcearis cum detractoribus,</hi> meddle not with them who are given to <hi>Detraction,</hi> he ſeemes as it were, <hi>obſtare prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiis,</hi> to ſtoppe the beginnings of Rebellion; and if ſome be carried away with that <hi>perverſitas fidei,</hi> that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſnes of faith, ſo as to beleive and give credit to the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction,</hi> then his, <hi>ne cum variis,</hi> ſtands good, meddle not with them who are given to <hi>Change,</hi> and if againe any be ſo far miſled as to deſire a <hi>Change,</hi> an alteration, or (if you will) a pretended reformation, yet, <hi>ne cum Seditioſis,</hi> by no meanes meddle with them who are given to <hi>Sedition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ne commiſcearis, meddle not,</hi> which forbids not only with <hi>Ioab</hi> to be generall, with <hi>Achitophell</hi> to be Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:30851:26"/>
with <hi>Sheba</hi> to be Trumpeter, with <hi>Abiather</hi> to be Prieſt, with the <hi>Citty Abell</hi> to be harbourer, with the <hi>men</hi> of <hi>Sichem</hi> to be Contributers, with the <hi>Congregation</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to be Approvers; but <hi>ne Commiſcearis,</hi> meddle not, have no part or portion with them; though they tell thee as it is Pro. 1.13.14. <hi>We ſhall find all pretious Subſtance, we ſhall fill our Houſes with ſpoyle, caſt in thy Lott amongſt us, let us all have one purſe;</hi> yet, ver. 15. <hi>My ſonne</hi> (that is, ſuch an one as he would have feare God and the King) <hi>walke not thou in the way with them, refraine thy foot from their path; meddle</hi> not, that is, <hi>riſe not up, corde,</hi> in the heart, by <hi>Conſenting; Lingua,</hi> with the Tongue, by <hi>Encouraging; Manu,</hi> with the Hand, by <hi>Acting, or Contributing.</hi> But why ſo? why, <hi>their calamity ſhall riſe ſuddenly, &amp;c.</hi> here is the <hi>malum culpae,</hi> and the <hi>malum paenae,</hi> the <hi>malum culpae</hi> the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil of Sin implyed, and the <hi>malum paenae</hi> the evil of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment expreſt, for Puniſhment ever preſuppoſeth Sinne, and by the greivouſnes of the Puniſhment, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the hainouſnes of the Sin. <hi>Their calamity,</hi> or <hi>their deſtruction,</hi> ſhall riſe <hi>ſuddenly,</hi> it ſhall not come <hi>lento,</hi> but <hi>cito pede,</hi> not with a ſlow but a ſwift pace, <hi>repente conſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get,</hi> it ſhall riſe ſuddenly; and ſuddain miſchiefes confound the mind, and fitly, when the mind is ſet upon confuſion. Yea <hi>conſurget</hi> alſo, it ſhall not only <hi>riſe up</hi> againſt them, but <hi>conſurget, riſe up</hi> with them, following their Sinne as the Shadow doth the Body. Thus <hi>their deſtruction ſhall riſe ſuddenly, &amp; ruinam eorum quis ſcit,</hi> and who knowes the Ruine of <hi>them both?</hi> both whom? why the Author and the Actor, the Rebell and the Rebell-Maker; the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractor, and him that gives credit to his wicked Detrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the innovator, and him that favours his unlawfull innovation; The Seditious, and him that meddles with his deteſtable Sedition; <hi>quis ſcit?</hi> who knows? rather <hi>quis
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:30851:27"/>
neſcit,</hi> who knowes not the end of a Traytor, the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of a Rebell? true, as concerning his temporall Ruine; but his eternall Ruine, <hi>quis ſcit,</hi> who knowes that? his Sufferings are ſutable to his Doings; there is a <hi>quis ſcit?</hi> for his Rebellious Actions, and not unfitly then a <hi>quis ſcit?</hi> for his juſt Sufferings The <hi>Praecipice</hi> of Rebellion is ſuch, that Seldome doth it ſtoppe till it come to the Bottome, even hell it ſelfe, where I wiſh it had beene long ſince chained. That (to the Glory and Praiſe of God, with the Peace and Proſperity of this Kingdome, and to the joy and happines of our King) we might ſay with Solomon, in the prayſe of our Soveraigne, as well as of his Subjects;
<q>Rex, in quem nemo inſurgit; A King, againſt whom there is no riſing up.</q>
            </p>
            <closer>Laus Deo.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Pag. <hi>10.</hi> lin. <hi>21.</hi> allowes r. allow, p. <hi>11.</hi> l. <hi>19.</hi> Strigellus, r. Strigellius. p. <hi>12.</hi> l. <hi>12.</hi> antiquam. r. antequam. p. <hi>14.</hi> l. <hi>17.</hi> hominum. r. hominem. p. <hi>14.</hi> l. <hi>24.</hi> propter r. praeter.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
